<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A retraction of separation wherein VI arguments formerly erected for the service of separation upon the account of infant baptisme are taken down, and VI other arguments for saints generall communion, though of different perswasion, are erected in their room : together with a patheticall swasive to unity, peace, and concord as our generation-work in speciall / by William Allen.</title>
            <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25232</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08801319</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08801319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41880</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41880)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1273:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A retraction of separation wherein VI arguments formerly erected for the service of separation upon the account of infant baptisme are taken down, and VI other arguments for saints generall communion, though of different perswasion, are erected in their room : together with a patheticall swasive to unity, peace, and concord as our generation-work in speciall / by William Allen.</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 71 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Crips,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Dr. Williams' Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41880:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RETRACTATION OF SEPARATION.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN VI Arguments formerly erected for the ſervice of <hi>Separation,</hi> upon the account of <hi>Infant Baptiſme,</hi> are taken down:</p>
            <p>AND VI Other Arguments for Saints generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, though of different perſwaſion, are erected in their room.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER WITH</hi> A patheticall Swaſive to unity, peace, and concord, as our generation-work in ſpeciall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM ALLEN.</p>
            <q>
               <p>When thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy brethren,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Luk. 22.32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Goe ye and learne what that meaneth, I will have mercy and not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 9.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Phil. 3.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace,</hi>
                  <bibl>Ro: 14.19.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Crips,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the entrance out of <hi>Lumbard</hi> ſtreete into <hi>Popes-head</hi>-Alley. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41880:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41880:2"/>
            <head>To the godly READERS, both <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Pedobaptiſts.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſcope of this little piece being in ſpeciall to cloſe the wound of diviſion that hath been made in the Church of God about <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> I ſhall here offer a word to both parts divided. Firſt, to the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> for ſo I call them, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that name whether proper or improper, by which they are beſt knowne among men. That which I would briefly ſay to them, partly reſpects their opinion, and partly their ſeparation about it.</p>
            <p>My humble requeſt to them; Firſt is, That their diſſent from other godly Chriſtians in the point of <hi>Infant Baptiſme,</hi> may be held and managed with much humility and ſobriety towards them that differ. That reverence which is due to the wiſdome, godlineſſe, faithfulneſſe and zeal of ſo great a number as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages have been, and in this preſent age are of a minde dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from them in this point, calls for it. The ſence of their owne weakneſſe, and that they are no more infallible then other men, calls for it. And the peace and undiſturbed ſtate of the Church and people of God, which every Chriſtian is bound as much as in him lies to preſerve, calls for it likewiſe.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe of them that Judge it their duty to uphold a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate ſtate upon account of this difference; my humble motion to them is, That they would read the enſuing Diſcourſe, or any other of like nature, with an open and free minde, and with that inclination to unity, peace, and concord, that ought to rule in the
<pb facs="tcp:41880:3"/>hearts of all Saints: and to give the arguments and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which oppoſe <hi>Separation,</hi> the ſame law and faire play in their judgements, which they have been wont to allow to their contrary: and that they would make as much, if not much more, conſcience to lay out and engage their thoughts how to remove ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt generall communion, of Saints, as to make them. Certainly the great cry of the Scripture for unity, peace, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and forbearance among Saints, and againſt their diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diviſions, and the experience of their ill effects, is a lowd call to this. And ſo is the law of true Evangelicall brotherly love, and the principle of it, in whom ſoever found, which is ſtill work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if not obſtructed, towards a kindly cloſure with all that have the like precious faith, and ſeed of God, remaining in them, and which makes them deſirous and glad of any helpe to remove out of the way, what ever keepes them from the cloſeſt communion.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe that are or ſhall be convinced of the undue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this <hi>Separation;</hi> and yet for fear of offending the weake, conceal their Judgement; my deſire and advice is, that they would ſet before them the blame which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by diſſembling his Judgement for fear of offending that ſort of believers which were of the Circumciſion, <hi>Gal: 2.11, 12, 13.</hi> beſides the account which I afterwards give, of my owne practice in the contrary.</p>
            <p>My prayer on the other hand to the godly <hi>Pedobaptiſts,</hi> both Miniſters and people, is, That they would uſe like moderation and tenderneſſe towards the godly <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> and not for their different opinion ſake in point of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> to ſet them at naught, and repreſent them to the people, and that without diſtinction, as ſuch monſters as ſome doe; nor to make an eſtimate or repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the beſt by the worſt, (there being neer as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> as there is between <hi>Pedobaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Pedobaptiſts;</hi>) but to think and ſpeak of them as ſuch, who for a conſiderable part of them, at leaſt, are truely tender of the glory of the Lord, and of the royall authority of his holy Lawes; and as deſirous to approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all good conſcience both to God and men; and as ſuch among whom there are as ſavoury and experimentall Chriſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:41880:3"/>as moſt in their generation. The want of this moderation in many of the <hi>Pedobaptiſts,</hi> I believe hath had a great hand in the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and ſeparations of our times; partly by ſetting them of the other Judgement at a further diſtance from them then otherwiſe they would have been; and partly by inclining many who have thought them wronged, to fall in with them and off from the other.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould be in an errour: yet certainly their opinion about <hi>Baptiſme</hi> after faith, cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed to be of that nature, if it ſhould be an errour, but that it may well conſiſt with an eminent degree of grace, as many I doubt not of different thoughts from them, doe ſufficiently expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. And with what heart then can any who know the worth of grace, and how to value perſons by it, make ſuch to be a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſtock to the people, for a ſuppoſed infirmity in judgement? Beſides; the ſtrong probabilities (not now to ſay proofes) which they have for their opinion; may well beſpeake a moderate and ſober treatment, from ſuch as diſſent. As to matter of fact: what can be ſaid to evince <hi>Infant Baptiſme</hi> a primitive practice, but may be ſo farre counter-argued, as to leave an enlightened and tender conſcience, without conviction in the caſe? And as to the reaſon of the thing: when it ſhall be argued that to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, is to be buried; and that buriall betokens or ſuppoſeth the perſon buried, to be dead, <hi>viz.</hi> unto ſin; and how incompetent ſuch a death is to an infant ſtate; and how prepoſtercus it is to bury perſons before they are dead: is it not very poſſible that when all is ſaid that can be ſaid to take away the ſtrength of ſuch a conſideration, that yet ſo much may be apprehended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne, by many a wiſe and holy man, as may hold his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence fast? And therefore why ſhould ſuch an opinion that hath ſo much to be ſaid for it, and hard to be anſwered, render its friends ſo criminall in the eyes, in the reports of their brethren, as ſometimes it does? Or if ſome that be of that opinion, have eſpouſed any other opinions of worſe import; yet why ſhould this be charged upon the whole Tribe? See <hi>Revel: 2.24. &amp; 3.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word; if the godly <hi>Pedobaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41880:4"/>would but charitably conſider what each plead for themſelves, and would but have their eyes more upon what is lovely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireable in each other, and be ready to owne and acknowledge it, and to provide a covering for each others infirmities, (which yet would be no works of ſupererogation, but their duty;) how ſoon would they delight in one another, and come cloſer together, and ſerve the Lord with one ſhoulder? and if thoſe of each ſubdiviſion among themſelves, would doe ſo too; what a heaven upon earth ſhould we have in compariſon of what now we have? But if each ſhall ſtill abound in their owne ſence, and impoſe that ſence upon one another; and ſhall ſtill be laying their fingers upon each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſores, and aggravating every ſmall matter, and conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things in the worst ſence, and harbouring jealouſies and evil ſurmiſings against one another, where there is no viſible ground; and in the mean while over-look the praiſe-worthy things that are viſible enough in many on both ſides; what can be expected but the baniſhing of charity, and with it peace and the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but the increaſe of emulations, contentions, diviſions, and with theſe errour, hereſie, and apoſtacie, untill we have ſo farre devoured one another, and our religion too, as at last to expoſe our ſelves and our profeſſion, Goſpel, Ordinances and liberties, as a prey to the common Enemy, whoſe hopes and endeavours of ſwallowing up all, are doubtleſſe nouriſhed and ſtrengthened by our diviſions. And what christian heart can beare the thought of being acceſſary to ſuch things as theſe?</p>
            <p>Where then there is any true affection left to the intereſt of Chriſt, and ſafety of ſouls, which are already ſo farre endama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and further endangered by the uncharitable contentions and diviſions of profeſſors; let it ſhew it ſelfe by a ſpeedy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate endeavour to finde out wayes and to improve opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of reconciling diſſenting brethren, upon the account of thoſe many and mayne things of faith and holineſſe, wherein they are already one, and which in reaſon ſhould ſway more to hold them faſt together, then thoſe few and farre leſſer things wherein they differ, ſhould to divide, ſcatter, and alienate them one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And ſo they would if there were no ſelfe-intereſt, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance about the doctrine of forbearance, or pride, or uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:41880:4"/>to hinder it; which Chriſtians ſhould abhorre, not cheriſh. Alas, <hi>ſhall the ſword alwayes devour?</hi> is <hi>there no balm in Gilead? is there</hi> no <hi>Phycian there?</hi> Muſt we ſit downe in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair? or muſt we waite on miracles to make Gods people on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? Surely if mens eyes were but a little more open, every one to ſee their owne ſin in making, or not cordially endeavouring the cure of our breaches; reconciliation w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld be found a work of no ſuch difficulty to effect among thoſe that are ſteered by Chriſts intereſt, (and thoſe that are not, let them be left out, they will but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard the work;) for they would be ſo much aſhamed of this ſin, and the diſ-ſervice they have done Chriſt by it, as that they would not be able to refraine mutuall endeavours on every hand to quench the flame that is kindled in the houſe of God, and to call upon one another to joyne herein. There's now ſome hopefull dawnings of ſuch a day by agitations now on foot; yet if while the Sun is but peeping out of one cloud, another ſhould come over it; let no mans heart or hand be weakened upon that account: if you will but <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after peace</hi> with all your might, you ſhall certainly at laſt over-take it and bring it back again: and I am ſure, its compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worth running for. <hi>Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one may edifie another,</hi> Rom: <hi>14.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Septemb. <hi>5th 1659.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41880:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41880:5"/>
            <head>A Retractation of Separation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſt wiſe and holy God, at firſt made and diſpoſed all his creatures in ſuch ſubordination and order, as that no diviſion either did or could befall them, through any defect in his workmanſhip. But the Devill, the originall Author and founder of diviſion and ſinfull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, having himſelfe firſt left his own place where God had ſet him, became head of a faction againſt God; and from that day to this, hath induſtriouſly endeavoured to work divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion between God and men, and among men themſelves. And <hi>for this cauſe was Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, made manifeſt, that he might deſtroy the works of the Devil;</hi> and counter-work him, in reconciling men to God, and one to another. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the cloſer men doe follow Chriſt, and the more they are acted by his Spirit, the more they are for unity and concord; for healing of breaches: and reconciling of divided parties. As on the other hand; the more men are acted and influenced by the ſpirit of Satan, the more they are for dividing worke. For theſe two Princes, the one of light, the other of darkneſſe, carry on their two contrary works of diviſion and union, by the agency of their followers.</p>
            <p>And yet the Devil does not carry on this work only by ſuch as are his, but ſo out-wits many well meaning men that deſigne ſerving of Chriſt and promoting of truth in the maine, as to make them think they are building up Gods truth and worſhip by ſeparation, when they are pulling downe his houſe which is the pillar thereof, by diviſion: and ſo do really accomodate the Devils deſigne, whilſt they intend the advancement of the cauſe of Chriſt. They think that ſome one particular truth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41880:6"/>which they apprehend to have diſcovered, will not be ſeen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in a croud of the contrary minded, (though of the ſame alliance to Chriſt) and therefore they get out of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that by the light of their ſeparation, that truth for which they doe ſeparate, might be the better ſeen and the more taken notice of, and the more prized, whilſt communion with them, cannot be had without it. But in the meane while they are not aware how they hinder Chriſts work, while they intend to promote it, and befriend the Devils deſigne, whilſt they intend to withſtand it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In hindering the reception of that truth if it be a truth, which they intend to propagate. For by ſuch a ſeparation, they render themſelves leſſe acceptable to them from whom they withdraw, then they were before, and more ſuſpected too: and ſo are at a greater diſadvantage to commend any truth to them, then they were before: Prejudice againſt the Preacher, begetting prejudice againſt his doctrine. For which cauſe alſo, all their other Chriſtian applications to them will be leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and leſſe effectuall, unleſſe there be a bundance of grace to prevent it; it faring with them in this caſe as it doth many times with men who take a kinde of conceit againſt good meat, for the unacceptableneſſe of the veſſell in which it is dreſſed, or diſh in which its brought: that's one way by which unawares, as I conceive, they gratifie the enemy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By ſuch diviſions and ſeparations of one part of Gods people from another, they lay themſelves open, and become obnoxious to the temptations and ſurpriſall of the enemy. Their ſtrength to withſtand the enemy, lies under God in their union and aſſociation. When the Apoſtle exhorts the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (<hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.) to ſtand faſt and to maintaine their ground againſt the enemy, he immediately directs them to <hi>[ſtrive to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether] for the faith of the Goſpel. And if one prevaile, yet two ſhall withſtand him; and a threefold cord, is not eaſily broken, Eccl.</hi> 4.12. But by dividing and ſeparating, they looſe their ſtrength, and become a prey to the enemy. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.7. <hi>I will divide them in Jacob, and ſcatter them in Iſrael:</hi> dividing makes way for ſcattering and overcoming. How eaſie a matter is it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41880:6"/>for an enemy by his united force to ſubdue the greateſt Armie when they ſhall fight him only in ſmall parties? he will firſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome one partie and then another, and ſo all one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And that doubtleſſe is the reaſon why the enemy hath ſo mightily prevailed, and taken ſo many that did wear Chriſts colours, priſoners, and led them away captive under the power and command of mand dangerous and deſtroying errors and hereſies, ſince thoſe unhappie diviſions and ſeparations among the people of God, have broken out and ſo abounded in this Nation. And therefore I conceive that upon true account it will be found, that where the enemy hath drawne away one other perſon to become a <hi>Quaker,</hi> or a <hi>Ranter,</hi> or the like, he hath drawne away many of thoſe that upon one account or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had before ſeparated themſelves in their communion, from a great part of the people of God. As ſtraglers from an Army uſe to fall into the hands of the enemy, when thoſe that abide in the mayne body are ſafe; even ſo is it with thoſe that ſtragle from the mayne body of Chriſt the univerſall Church in their communion, they are gathered up by the enemy, here one and there one, when in the meane while thoſe that abide and keep their rancks in the mayne body, are more generally kept ſafe. Doubtleſſe its not much leſſe dangerous for Saints to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from Saints upon account of their differences, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what advantage is given the enemy thereby, then it would be for an Army who all engage for the ſame cauſe in the maine, to divide and part upon account of difference among them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout wearing of Colours, or ordering themſelves, when they have a potent and reſolved enemy in the field ready to fight them.</p>
            <p>For beſides the danger already hinted, by ſuch ſeparation they take courſe to diſ-arme themſelves, at leaſt in great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and to put weapons into the enemies hand. Chriſtian Charity is in great part a Chriſtians ſecurity; and the ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I ſpeake of, tends greatly to weaken and by degrees to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy that charity, as I ſhall ſhew afterward. To what degree the enemy draws any of us out of Chriſtian charity, he draws us out of our ſtrong hold and place of ſecurity. <hi>If we love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41880:7"/>God dwelleth in us,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>and he that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in God, and God in him,</hi> (1 John 4.12, 16.) and therefore muſt needs be ſafe. If God dwell in him, it is to govern and guide him, to ſupport and uphold him, to ſave and defend him. Where God dwells, light and ſtrength dwells. <hi>He that loveth his brother abideth in the light, and there is none occaſion of ſtumbling in him,</hi> 1 John 2.10. But uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is quite contrary to God who is love; and where that dwells, he takes no pleaſure to dwell: and if he who is the Chriſtians ſafety, ſtrength and guide, be but withdrawne; what can be expected but darkneſſe, weakneſſe, wandering, and the enemies enterin, and taking poſſeſſion. <hi>He that hateth his brother, is in darkneſſe, and walketh in darkneſſe, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not whither he goeth, becauſe darkneſſe hath blinded his eyes,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.11. Uncharitableneſſe, then, deprives men of Gods preſence, which is their only ſafety, and makes way for the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and ſo betrayes them into the hand of errour and deluſion. <hi>The end of the Commandment</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>is charity, from which ſome having ſwerved, have turned aſide to vain jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.5, 6. Turning aſide to vain langling, is that which followes the ſwerving from charity. As love departs, ſo jangling, errour and confuſion takes place. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 19. <hi>I hear there are diviſions among you, and I partly believe it: for there muſt be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, may be made manifeſt.</hi> The Apoſtle knowing there muſt come hereſies among them, was eaſily induced to believe the report that brought him news of the diviſions in that Church; as looking upon thoſe, but as preparing and making way for the other. If you hear of much contention among brethren, once, for want of charity; expect to hear of hereſies among them ere long. Seaſons of uncharitable contentions among Chriſtian brethren, are gainfull advantages for the Devil to deceive in. Mark and conſider that Propheſie of Chriſt; <hi>Mat:</hi> 24, 10, 11, 12. <hi>Then ſhall many be offended and ſhall betray one anoeher, and ſhall hate one another. And many falſe Prophets ſhall riſe and ſhall deceive many.</hi> When Chriſts followers fall a hating and ſo a betraying one another, then the Devil ſends forth his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41880:7"/>Prophets as the fitteſt ſeaſon poſſible to carry away many of thoſe which were growne in diſtaſt with their godly brethren. <hi>And becauſe iniquity</hi> in this kinde, <hi>ſhall abound, the love of many ſhall wax cold,</hi> ver. 12. A great decay of affection to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel takes place, when uncharitableneſſe, errour, and Apoſtacy among the profeſſors thereof, doth abound. And may not I ſay as Chriſt in another caſe ſometimes ſaid? <hi>This day is this Scripture fulfilled in your ears.</hi> For when the godly among the Epiſcoparians, Presbyterians, Independents, and Anabaptiſts, fell to ſiding, party againſt party; and envie, emmulations, and uncharitableneſſe increaſed, then the Devill thruſts out a great variety of ſeducers that have carryed away many into wayes of dangerous errour, eſpecially of thoſe that have proceeded fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt in ſeparation by ſeveral ſubdiviſions. Though God hath in the meane while graciouſly kept ſuch as have retained a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall love to all the people of God, and have managed their differences with more moderation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another way by which Separation of Saints from Saints furthers Satans and hinders Chriſts deſigne, (what ever they themſelves deſigne by it) is in hindering the ſucceſſe of the Goſpel in its converting work. For by it unbeliefe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in ungodly men, is nouriſhed and maintained. The Saints differences, though but in ſome leſſer matters, when made ſo publique and notorious by ſeparations, doe gratifie the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving thoughts which ſinfull men have, as if the Goſpel were an uncertain thing. When they ſee thoſe that pretend to ſo much knowledge of it, to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agree in matters ſo materiall, as thoſe that concern their owning one another as Chriſtian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, they think (its like) that they may ſuſpend a thorow beliefe of the whole. Chriſt prayed that all thoſe that ſhould believe through his Apoſtles word, might <hi>be one that the world might believe,</hi> John 17.21. They are thoſe that bear witneſſe before the world that the Goſpel is true: but to what degree (as in all Courts) the witneſſes diſagree; their teſtimony is weakened, and their evidence ſuſpected. When their Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet by which they ſhould al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m the world, gives an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſound, who ſhall prepare himſelfe to the battell? They
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41880:8"/>know not what religion to be of, they ſay, and will ſee profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors better agreed, before they will be reſolvedly and thorowly of any. It was the Devils policie of old to raiſe up falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in oppoſition to the true, that while one ſaid one thing, and another another thing in the name of the Lord, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people might be amuſed, and not know which to follow. And its much to be feared, that he gaines much of the ſame advantage by the declared publiſhed contradictions among the Saints. Hence is the common complaint touching the paucity of converts, now adayes. There's much preaching and much diſcourſive knowledge, but how rare are thoſe effectuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions that the Word accompanied with the peace, charity, and ſincerity of Saints in former times, did produce. Now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed men are converted from one opinion in Religion to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but to have ſtout-hearted ſinners to fall at the feet of Jeſus Chriſt by the power of his Word, and giant-like tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors to become like weaned children, I believe (and its not my thought alone) is a ſight farre more rare to behold now, then formerly. And why? Surely not becauſe the Word is leſſe quick and powerfull now then it was then; but becauſe its now more hindered, and clogged by the diviſions, ſeparations, and contrary opinions of profeſſors, and ſcandalls concurring, then formerly it was.</p>
            <p>And as theſe diviſions and ſeparations have hindered the converſion of ſome, ſo doubtleſſe have they occaſioned the ſubverſion of many others, who have ſtumbled at this ſtumbling ſtone, and forſaken the tents of the Saints of all perſwaſions; turning, ſome Quakers, ſome Ranters, and Libertines, ſome Papiſts, and ſome Atheiſts. Papiſts and Atheiſts there were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for, but for ſtrict profeſſors of godlineſs to become ſuch, was, I think, ſeldome ſeen before. The frequent interreſſing the weake in doubtfull diſputations, hath been like the putting of new wine into old bottles, or the ſewing of a new piece of cloth to an old garment; the wine hath been ſpilt, and the rent made worſe: their heads have turned round with the noiſe of abundance of contrary arguings, of which they have not been able to make judgement. And upon that account have been
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41880:8"/>tempted to taſt of every water, to be experiencing every way; trying every thing, till at laſt they have come to nothing. Such open and violent ſtrivings about things of doubtfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, as to ſet one Chriſtian at a diſtance from another, hath proved a ſad occaſion of ſubverting the hearers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like have been the effects of the late yeares diviſions and ſeparations of Saints, though better things then theſe, I doubt not, have been intended by them. And if there hath been any diſcovery of truth by our contendings; yet I doubt by the ill managing of our differences, if the account could be caſt up, the loſſe in the totall, in relation to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Chriſt, would be found much more then the gaine. And I muſt now ſay, that the experience, obſervation and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration of ſuch things as theſe, hath occaſioned me to review my Arguments for Separation with a jealous eye; and hath prepared the way for ſuch Arguments and Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as plead the cauſe of generall communion among all Saints, to have the readier acceſſe to my underſtanding. And after ſome moneths labour in this ſearch, accompanied with ſerious ſeeking of God about this matter, I have at laſt found cauſe (as I have verily thought) to accuſe my ſelfe before the Lord, as one too greatly acceſſary to the miſchievous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of diviſion and ſeparation; and that not only in practiſing the way of ſeparation my ſelfe, but alſo in ſtrengthening the hands of others thereto by pleading that cauſe in print. In the ſence of which, together with other my manifold weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, I have through grace humbled my ſelfe, and deſire to lie low before the Lord all my dayes. Giving him glory for his great mercy towards me in that preſence and thoſe ſupplies of his which he hath been pleaſed graciouſly to vouchſafe me, during the time of this miſtake, my weakneſſe and unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe notwithſtanding: and now at laſt to deliver me from thoſe crooked thoughts (as I humbly iudge them to have been) which cauſed me to breake communion with thoſe Chriſtian Brethren and children of my father, that were not of my minde in the points of Infant and after-baptiſme. Shall I ſay the Lord
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41880:9"/>had mercy on me becauſe I did it ignorantly! for I verily thought my ſelfe in a way of ſerving both God and men, in what I did therein.</p>
            <p>I am not unſencible but that this alteration of thought and way in me; though but in the point of communion, is for the preſent, matter of offence and griefe to many, whoſe griefe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account cannot but be griefe to me, and whom to pleaſe in any thing, in which I ſhould not diſpleaſe the Lord, would be farre more acceptable to me. I have conſidered alſo, that ſome weak ones will be in danger of ſtumbling and taking hurt thereby; for whoſe ſakes I have been the more graduall, ſlow, and tender in diſcovering and putting in execution my change of thoughts in this particular. And it hath been no ſmall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me, (the Lord knowes,) that my former unadviſedneſſe, ſhould put me upon a neceſſity of running ſuch hazards. But when I have conſidered that there is a neceſſity upon him that hath gone out of the right way, more or leſſe, to returne into it, when he comes to know it: and that a man may by no meanes make himſelfe acceſſary to a certain evil in himſelfe, to prevent a contingent and accidentall one in another: and that the probable dangers in relation to others in upholding ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, are more then thoſe that attend the taking it downe; and that where one miſcarries by the latter, many fall by the former: And conſidering alſo, that I am under a publiſhed engagement in one of my Epiſtles, to retract what formerly I have done, upon condition of an after-diſcovery of vanity therein; I have thought it my duty, not only to make that late retreat; but alſo to be as publick in my returne out of the way of ſeparation, as I was in my entrance into it: as judging it not impoſſible, but that God in time may make uſe of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to lead or at leaſt to keep as many and many more out of the way of ſeparation, then ever my former writings for ſeparation, led into it. However having herein done what I judged my duty, I ſhall commit the iſſue and ſucceſſe to God.</p>
            <p>To vindicate then my preſent-practice of free communion with reformed godly Congregations of Pedobaptiſts; but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41880:9"/>much more to perſwade others to joyne with me therein, I ſhall through Gods aſſiſtance endeavour theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To take downe thoſe Arguments by which I once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to build up Separation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Propoſe ſome Arguments to evince the lawfulneſſe of Church-communion between the godly, both Pedobaptiſts and Anabaptiſts, and the unlawfulneſſe of denying their communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one with another upon account of their baptiſmall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. In the doing of which, I ſuppoſe, I ſhall have occaſion to conſider all that is conſiderable on the other hand, either of Arguments or Objections. Which done, I hope will be of good uſe to cure and prevent the evill of Separation of godly from godly upon other accounts alſo as well as this.</p>
            <div type="arguments">
               <head>My ſix former Arguments for Separation, taken downe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, I would here give notice, that my ſix Arguments, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly publiſhed, in countenance of Separation of godly from godly upon the account of Infant Baptiſme, are laid downe for the moſt part rather Motive-wiſe, then Argument-wiſe; and doe not rationally conclude the thing for which they were brought. I ſhall therefore contract and reduce them in the beſt of their ſtrength, into form of Argument, and then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover in what reſpects they are inconcludent of the poſition touching Separation, which ſhould have been proved by them.</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <p>Firſt Argument for Separation, is to this effect.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe Churches may not be held communion with, in whoſe conſtitution ſuch a part of the foundation of Chriſtian Churches as the doctrine of Baptiſme mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. is wanting.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch are the beſt of the Churches of the Pedobaptiſts. Therefore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it is the duty of every Chriſtian, ſo farre as he contributes any thing towards the erecting a houſe for Chriſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41880:10"/>therein according to the beſt of his underſtanding, and as much as in him lies, to endeavour that it be built according to the pattern in the Mount, I mean the Scriptures; and that no part of the foundation through his default be left out; I eaſily grant and ſtill aſſert. But that that part of the foundation which conſiſts in the doctrine of Baptiſme, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. is wholly wanting in the Churches of the Pedobaptiſts, I doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: or if there be ſome part of it wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing in them; yet that ſuch a partiall defect is any ſufficient ground of ſeparation from them, I doe alſo deny, and ſhall here offer ſomething to ſhew that it is a great miſtake ſo to think.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That part of the foundation which conſiſts in the <hi>[doctrine] of Baptiſme,</hi> is not totally wanting in the Aſſemblies of the godly Pedobaptiſts. For about the <hi>[doctrine]</hi> of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, the Pedobaptiſts doe agree with the Anabaptiſts in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weighty points, though they differ in ſome other. 1. They both agree that water Baptiſme is an ordinance inſtituted by the Lord. And 2. To be continued in the uſe of it to the end of the world. 3. That all that are converted from another to the Chriſtian religion and profeſſion, ought upon ſuch conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to be baptized, as thoſe whoſe Baptiſme after faith is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Scripture were. 4. That to be baptized is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed putting on of Chriſt, and that Baptiſme is a badge of Chriſts profeſſed Diſciples, diſtinguiſhing them from ſuch as doe not own Chriſt. 5. That all that are baptized, are thereby obliged to ceaſe living any more to ſin, but are bound thereby to live a new and holy life unto God. 6. That all the Diſciples of Chriſt ought actually to be under this ingagement. In all theſe they both agree. 7. As the one hold themſelves actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engaged to the lawes of Chriſt by their Baptiſme after faith, ſo doe the other by that which they account a ſufficient Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, though received before faith. 8. As the one doe the things to which Goſpel-Baptiſme does oblige, ſo doe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Although then the Pedobaptiſts be ſuppoſed to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in the doctrine of Baptiſme in relation to ſome of the ſubjects of it, (and it is but ſome) and likewiſe in relation to the form of adminiſtration; yet agreeing in ſo many of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41880:10"/>ſubſtantiall parts of the doctrine of Baptiſme as is before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; we cannot ſay juſtly, that there is an utter failer in them as to this part of the foundation. There are two parts of the doctrine of Baptiſme; the one concernes <hi>the putting away of the filth of the fleſh;</hi> the other <hi>the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God, by the reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead.</hi> If they are defective in that part of the doctrine which concernes the putting away the filth of the fleſh, yet they are orthodox and ſound in that part which concernes the anſwer of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God; which according to the Apoſtle, is the greater and better part, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. A partiall defect, and that too in the leſſer part of the foundation, does not make a nullity in it; no more then the want of a hand, or an eye, or a leg, makes a man to be no man. And if a woman ſhould ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from her husband when wanting any of theſe, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that he is no man, ſhe would not be held innocent. Defects in and about holy things, though great and notable, doe not alwayes cauſe a privation of the ends of the holy things themſelves. The manner of <hi>Jacobs</hi> obtaining the bleſſing, was greatly defective, and full of ſinfull mixture, but yet did not nullifie the bleſſing it ſelfe. It was a great defect in the Office of high Prieſthood, when God would have but one high Prieſt at one time, and him during life, (<hi>Num.</hi> 35.25, 28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.23.) for men to ſet up two, or elſe to make an annuall electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: (<hi>Joh.</hi> 11.49, 51. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.6.) but yet who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thought for all that, that all the adminiſtrations of ſuch an high Prieſt were nullities, and that no body was the better for them?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Its a great miſtake likewiſe, to think that every partiall defect in the foundation of a compleat Church conſtitution, is a ſufficient ground of ſeparation. For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Its very probable that ſomething of that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in the doctrine of Baptiſme, a part of the foundation <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. is wanting (as it was enioyed in the primitive Church) in the beſt conſtituted and well ordered Church at this day in the world. For when the Author of that Epiſtle ſpeakes of the doctrine of <hi>[Baptiſmes]</hi> in the plurall number, what can we ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41880:11"/>reaſonably underſtand by it, beſides the Baptiſme of water, as the Baptiſme of the Spirit? And however all that are Chriſts, have his Spirit, (<hi>Rom:</hi> 8.9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.) yet I have as I think elſe-where rendred it probable from <hi>Mat.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Doubt reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>p.</hi> 37.</note> 3.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.3.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.16. compared, that the Baptiſme of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, was a priviledge peculiar to the primitive times, and is not now enjoyed by any that we know of: Wherein alſo I know I have the concurrant judgement of many of the Baptiſts at leaſt. So that its probable, all Churches this day in being, as well of the Anabaptiſts as of the Pedobaptiſts, are without this part of the foundation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Its as probable likewiſe that this Church of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> or at leaſt the Hebrew Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was the firſt Chriſtian Church in the world, in many of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, were without another part of the foundation men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Heb:</hi> 6. except the doctrine concerning it; and that is that <hi>of laying on of hands.</hi> By which underſtanding (according to the uſuall and moſt commonly received interpretation) the impoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion of hands upon baptized Diſciples in order to their receiving the holy Ghoſt, there's good cauſe to conceive that many in that Church never had hands layd on them for that end. For I conceive no man will think that the Apoſtles, much leſſe any others, did lay their hands upon any Diſciples for their receiving the holy Ghoſt till the day of Penticoſt, in which they themſelves received it. And the holy Ghoſt being then given to all the Diſciples then and there in being, and that in an extraordinary meaſure as well as manner; (<hi>Acts</hi> 2.) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that no man will think that the Apoſtles or others did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards lay their hands on any of thoſe Diſciples for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the holy Ghoſt, which they had upon ſuch excellent termes already. And yet of theſe was that Church firſt found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unto whom the new converts were afterwards added. So that the firſt Chriſtian Church in the firſt conſtitution of it, was (in all appearance of reaſon) wholly without this part of the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndation which is called one of the ſix principles of the doctrine of Chriſt, and afterward ſo remained in that part of it of which it was firſt formed. The like, I ſuppoſe, may be ſaid
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41880:11"/>of the firſt Chriſtian Church of the Gentiles at <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> Acts 10. who received the holy Ghoſt in like manner as the firſt Hebrew Church did, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.15.</p>
                  <p>If then the want or abſence of any though a leſſer part of the foundation mentioned <hi>Heb:</hi> 6. were a ſufficient ground or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſeparation from a Church in whoſe conſtitution ſuch part is wanting, then it had been the duty of the three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. to have kept at a diſtance from the hundred and twenty Diſciples, in ſtead of being added to them, ſince one part of that foundation in the letter of it, was not to be found in their conſtitution. And if neither the want of one of the Baptiſmes; nor the want of laying on of hands, both which are part of the foundation mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. be no ſufficient ground of ſeparation; it paſſes my skill, I confeſſe, ſince I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered it, to evince a defect in, yea or a meer want of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall part of the doctrine of Baptiſme, to be a juſt ground of ſeparation or deniall of communion, when ſuch defect or want proceeds not from a diſobedient will, but from an errour in Judgement coupled with an upright heart and ſoundneſſe of faith in the mayne principles of the Goſpel. And I would pray our Brethren that it may be conſidered, where the Lord hath commanded ſeparation or deniall of communion any more for the want of the one, then for the want of the other; and that we make no ſuch haſt to withdraw from our brethren, unleſſe God had bid us to doe ſo.</p>
                  <p>It will be ſufficient for us to follow the Lord, and to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw when he withdraws: but it does not become us to goe before him, and to withdraw where he abides. Where Chriſt the only foundation is ſincerely held in the mayne doctrines of Juſtification and Sanctification, there the Lord dwells in the grace of his preſence, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 6.56. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.12, 16.) though otherwiſe there may be ſome ſpots of deformity and blemiſhes in reſpect of the externall form of his houſe, as well as in the converſation otherwiſe. And if God can dwell there and yet not approve of ſuch defects by his preſence with them, ſo may his ſervants too. The Lord vouchſafes his preſence in ſuch Churches, in order to their help and healing, and ſo ſhould his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41880:12"/>ſervants. An honeſt man will not refuſe his wifes ſociety, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome bodily or morall infirmities, as long as ſhe is loyall to him in the mayne, but by his continuance with her, endeavour her help and cure.</p>
                  <p>Its true; it would be more acceptable and pleaſant to well-growne Saints, to be yoked in their communion, only with ſuch as are full of ſpirituall health and beauty. As it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be thought that it would be a thing more delightfull to Chriſt Jeſus, to converſe onely with creatures of an Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall perfection, if he had not healing-work to doe. But if Chriſt ſhould pleaſe himſelfe in the one; what would become of us? and if the beſt of Saints ſhould pleaſe themſelves in the other; what would become of the ſpiritually weak and ſickly? But behold thus it is written, and this is our pattern: <hi>Wee then that are ſtrong, ought to beare the infirmities of the weake, and not to pleaſe our ſelves; — for even Chriſt pleaſed not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>Rom:</hi> 15.1, 3.) You may know what's moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and unacceptable to the Lord hereabout, by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4. <hi>The diſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthened; neither have ye healed that which was ſick, neither have ye bound up that which was broken, neither have brought aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne that which was driven away, neither have ſought that which was loſt.</hi> Separating from them is not the way to cure them. If they have but a ſpirituall being; that which will but deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate them new creatures: well may their miſtakes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities put them under the greater neceſſity of your help, and you under the greater obligation of abounding ſo much the more in your tender, compaſſionate, and diligent applications for their increaſe in ſpirituall light, health, and ſtrength, but are farre from priviledging you to withdraw your communion from them. <hi>For God hath tempered the body together, having given more abundant honour to that part which lacked; that there ſhould be no ſchiſme in the body,</hi> 1 Cor: 12.24, 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>Second Argument for Separation, thus:</head>
                  <p>If the primitive believers aſſociated themſelves in Church-communion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41880:12"/>with none but ſuch as were baptized after profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of faith, then we may not. But the primitive believers did aſſociate themſelves in Church-communion with none but ſuch as were baptized after profeſſion of faith. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I doe acknowledge that all ſuch unbaptized per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then in being as the primitive believers would not have or had not communion with, we may not now have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with their like; and that what was a reaſon unto them not to have communion with ſuch, ought to be a reaſon to us of our non-communion in like caſe. And yet I utterly deny the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the Major propoſition; It will not follow that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the primitive believers had communion with none but ſuch as were baptized after faith, therefore we may have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with none but ſuch as are baptized after profeſſion of faith. And the reaſon of the inconfecuence is taken from the difference of perſons then and now. There is a great difference in the qualification of the perſons that had no Baptiſme, and ſo no Church-communion then, and many of the perſons that have no Baptiſme after profeſſion of faith now, and ſo the reaſon of non-communion varies accordingly. Thoſe in the primitive times that had no Baptiſme, and ſo no Church-communion, had no faith, nor made confeſſion of any. So that the reaſon of the primitive Saints non-communion with ſuch, was not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their want of Bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me, but their want of faith. And the ſame non-qualification now would be a like reaſon unto us of non-communion. But where perſons have faith, and this faith viſible in their profeſſion and converſation, and have alſo the doctrine of Baptiſme in the ſpirituall part of it, both in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice, and are confident they practically have, it too in the litterall part, which is the caſe of the godly Pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, there the difference is exceeding broad and large be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and thoſe unbaptized perſons with whom the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Saints had no communion; and ſo the ſame reaſon of non-communion will not ſuite both. If the primitive Saints had no communion with ſuch as the godly Pedobaptiſts; it was not becauſe they judged ſuch unworthy their communion, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was none ſuch then in being; that particular diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41880:13"/>between Saints and Saints about Infant Baptiſme, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then on foot; but if there had, I ſhall offer reaſon preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to induce us to believe that communion with them would not have been refuſed by the beſt of Saints then in being, on that ground.</p>
                  <p>In the meane time let it be conſidered, that we have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the primitive Saints refuſing communi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n with ſuch as the godly Pedobaptiſts are, and therefore by their example cannot be obliged to refuſe communion with them: their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of non-communion with unbaptized unbelievers, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne and irrelative to our caſe and queſtion, and therefore it is altogether impertinent in its allegation.</p>
                  <p>But if there were or had been any ſuch in the primitive times, as the godly Pedobaptiſts are; yet that we may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that the beſt of Saints in thoſe times would not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed communion with them, I ſhall offer theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We have no approved example of their refuſing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with any acknowledged godly Chriſtians whatſoever, for any errour in Judgment, or errour in practice proceeding meerly from an errour in Judgment: and therefore this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed errour of the godly Pedobaptiſts being but of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we have no reaſon to think that they would have found harder meaſure if they had then lived amongſt them, then all others erring upon like termes, did. And here let it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
                     </label> that our ſeparation of godly from godly upon account of ſuch errours as are not repugnant to godlineſſe, is ſo farre from being an imitation of the example of the primitive Saints, as that we have the example of the primitive Saints point blanck againſt it which may be a good argument to condemne, but by no meanes to juſtifie our ſeparation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When there was any thing ſtirring among the primitive Saints that did but tend to or looke towards a ſeparation upon account of ſuch errours as were not repugnant to godlineſſe, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id not paſſe without check and diſcountenance from the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſtles, as is viſible in the caſes of difference about Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, dayes, and meats, (of which more afterwards) And therefore the ſuppoſed errour of the Pedobaptiſts being but of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41880:13"/>the ſame nature; that is conſiſtent with godlineſſe as well as theirs, there's no reaſon to think it would have caſt them out of communion then when the looke of ſuch a thing in other like caſes, was ſo diſtaſtfull to the holy Apoſtle.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When the Apoſtle comes to lay downe and ennumerate the cauſes and things for which communion with a profeſſor of Chriſtianity is to be refuſed, there is none of them of a lower nature or leſſe demerit, then ſuch as doe exclude a man the kingdome of God, as is evident by comparing 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.11. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.9, 10. as by the meer reciting of the words will appeare. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.11. <hi>But now I have written unto you, not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother be a fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or covetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner, with ſuch an one, no not to eat.</hi> That every one of theſe crimes debarre a man the kingdome of God is evident by 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Know ye not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God? Be not deceived: neither fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, — nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, ſhall inherit the kingdome of God.</hi> And where ever withdrawing from, avoiding or rejecting of a profeſſor of the Goſpel, is enjoyned the Chriſtian brethren, you will ſtill finde it is either for crimes of a morall nature, either in kinde or end, or hereſie; but never for miſpriſion of Judgment about Ordinances, and matters of doubtfull diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among the Saints. Peruſe for this 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.—5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Rom:</hi> 16.17, 18. 2 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 3.6.11. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10, 11. By ought then that can be gathered from the Apoſtles writings, an errour of that nature which is charged upon the Pedobap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, would not have deprived godly perſons of the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints in the Apoſtles dayes. Which is a thing ſeriouſly to be laid to heart by them that are acceſſary to the keeping up a ſeparation, contrary to the doctrine, cuſtome and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the primitive times.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>Third Argument for Separation, runs thus.</head>
                  <p>None are in a regular capacity of holding Church commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41880:14"/>with a particular Church, who are not regularly viſible members of the univerſall Church.</p>
                  <p>But none but ſuch as are baptized after faith, which the Pedobaptiſts are not, are regularly viſible members of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Church. Therefore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That none are in a regular capacity of communion in a particular Church, who are not viſibly members of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall Church, I readily grant. And as to that clauſe which ſpeakes of mens being regularly viſible members of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Church, I ſay thus much: That none can be viſibly mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the univerſall Church, but ſo farre as they are ſo, they are regularly ſo: for no irregularity whatſoever as ſuch, can contribute towards the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>bility of a mans Church-member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but obſcure it. It is very true, that there may be more of reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>larneſſe in the viſibility of ſomes univerſall Church-memberſhip, then in others; and ſo proportionably more of viſibleneſſe; but where ever there is this viſibleneſſe in a greater or leſſer degree, there is ſo much regularneſſe of that viſibility.</p>
                  <p>Having ſaid thus much by way of conceſſion to the major propoſition, and that much for the explication of an imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent expreſſion touching the regular viſibility of univerſall Church-memberſhip, I come now to deny the Minor propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition which does affirm, that none but ſuch as are baptized after faith, are regularly viſible members of the univerſall Church: and doe affirm, that the godly Pedobaptiſts are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly members of the univerſall Church, though not baptized after profeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on of faith: and being ſo, have right to particular Church-memberſhip.</p>
                  <p>Whatever it is that gives us ground to judge any of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dobaptiſts godly, or men fearing God, makes their univerſall Church-memberſhip viſible. For there are no godly men or holy men, who are not members of Chriſts body: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for the ſame reaſon for which we judge any godly, we muſt judge them of the body or Church of Chriſt, if we doe but know and underſtand what we judge. But touching the viſibility of the univerſall Church-memberſhip of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41880:14"/>Pedobaptiſts, and of their right to communion in particular Churches thereby, I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly and fully in my firſt Argument for generall communion among Saints, and therefore ſhall ſay no more of it here, but referre you thither.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>Fourth Argument for Separation, ſtands thus:</head>
                  <p>If according to Goſpel order, all Chriſts Diſciples ought firſt to be baptized before they be admitted unto Church-communion, then the godly Pedobaptiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, although the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt, not being baptized, cannot be admitted to ſuch communion, without breach of Goſpel order.</p>
                  <p>But according to Goſpel order, all Chriſts Diſciples ought firſt to be baptized before they be admitted unto Church-communion. Therefore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I freely grant with all my heart that it is the order of Chriſt Jeſus in the Goſpel that his Diſciples ſhould firſt be baptized before they deſire or claime communion in a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church: For baptizing is that which next followes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling according both to the Commiſſion of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. and the conſtant recorded practice of the primitive times. And ſo farre the Argument holds good, that if any godly Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dobaptiſt or other Diſciple of Chriſt, ſhould deſire Church-communion before he is baptized as Chriſt would have him baptized, having opportunity of being ſo, he ſhould therein make himſelfe a tranſgreſſor of that order. And yet for all that it will not follow but that the godly Pedobaptiſts may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Church-communion by the Anabaptiſts, without any breach of Goſpel order on their part that doe ſo admit them.</p>
                  <p>And therefore I diſtinguiſh upon that phraſe <hi>[without breach of Goſpel order]</hi> mentioned in the cloſe of the conſequence of the Major propoſition, as it relates to the admiſſion of the godly Pedobaptiſts to communion. 1. As it reſpects the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons themſelves to be admitted, the propoſition is true; upon ſuppoſition that the godly Pedobaptiſts ſhould prove not to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41880:15"/>be baptized, then it would be a breach of the Goſpel order aforeſaid on their part, to claime Church-communion before they are baptized. But 2. If that paſſage <hi>[cannot be admitted to ſuch communion without breach of Goſpel order]</hi> be underſtood as reſpecting the Anabaptiſts as perſons admitting; then I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the conſequence of the Major propoſition is falſe, and that it will be no breach of Goſpel order on their part to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch to their communion, but indeed a conforming to and a faithfull obſerving of Goſpel order, viſible in other parts of the New Teſtament ſo to doe. For</p>
                  <p>There is no Goſpel order that I know of, that enjoynes bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized believers in no caſe to admit believers that are not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, into their communion: and <hi>where there is no law there is no tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom: 4.15. And if Chriſt have made no ſuch law, I am ſure it will not become us to make any ſuch. When I formerly built up that way of Separation which now I am la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to take downe, my ſoule made diligent ſearch for ſome Scripture forbidding the baptized to hold communion with unbaptized believers. And among all which I thought looked that way, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. is the chiefe, <hi>Goe teach</hi> or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple <hi>all nations, baptizing them.</hi> Which being againe looked into, I finde that all that can be gathered from it hereabout is onely this; that Chriſt would have all thoſe to be baptized, that ſhould be made Diſciples; or at moſt to be baptized next after diſcipling. Theſe words containe onely a law about diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling and baptizing, but nothing at all about communion: they enjoyne what ſhall be done in the one, but forbid nothing to be done in the other. As for the Diſciples after behaviour, it is concerned in the next words following, <hi>ver:</hi> 20. <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you, viz:</hi> to teach them. If then it did appeare that the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Apoſtles to teach the Diſciples when once bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, not to admit any unbaptized Diſciples of his to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in no caſe, then indeed it would be unlawfull for them ſo to doe. But till that do appeare, we had need to take heed of making voyd another command of the Lord, that we might eſtabliſh our own tradition inſtead of his command, in this.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41880:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But is not the conſtant order which the primitive Saints obſerved, a Goſpel order? and was it not their conſtant order without ſo much as once varying it, to receive onely ſuch into Church-fellowſhip and communion, as were before baptized? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.13. And would it not then be a viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Goſpel order to doe otherwiſe now?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I doe not know but that it was their conſtant order as to matter of fact to receive only baptized Diſciples into Church-communion: nor do I think but that under the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of their caſe, what they did in that kinde, was a Goſpel order; and that under the ſame circumſtances to doe otherwiſe now, would be a violation of Goſpel order. And yet for all that, this their primitive order of non-admiſſion of unbaptized, does not binde up the Anabaptiſts to a non-admiſſion of the godly Pedobaptiſts to their communion, where the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of non-admiſſion is not in being.</p>
                  <p>For it is not the meer fact and literall practice of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Saints ſimply conſidered, that is now binding to us; but the reaſon of it. Men that are not under the ſame reaſon of count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing which they poſſeſſe their owne, are not under the ſame obligation of ſelling their poſſeſſions and parting with them, as the primitive Saints were, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. Nay which is more, this is not only true in reſpect of practice and example, but of ſome precepts alſo: there were ſome precepts which were binding to them then, which are not ſo among us now, and that upon this very ground, becauſe the reaſon of them is nor in being to us as it was to them. As for example, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.17, 18. <hi>But thou when thou faſteſt, annoint thine head and waſh thy face, that thou appeare not unto men to faſt.</hi> This though the expreſſe command of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſt to his Diſciples, yet is not bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us in the letter of it, becauſe the cuſtome of the places where thoſe Diſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les lived and we now live, do vary ſo much, as that the reaſon of the precept would be croſſed ſhould the letter of it be obſerved. And ſurely it is for like reaſon that we doe not hold the holy kiſs, (1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5.26.) and the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Saints feet, (<hi>John</hi> 13.) and ſome other things of like nature, though expreſsly enjoyned, to be ſo obliging to us as to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41880:16"/>the primitive Saints. And upon what other ground elſe could the 120 Diſciples (<hi>Acts</hi> 1.) be any more excuſed from having hands laid on them, (ſuppoſing it in it ſelfe a duty in thoſe times as part of the foundation <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.2.) then other primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Saints, but onely that the end and reaſon of it was not in being to them, as it was to others. Upon like ground therefore I think we may ſafely conclude, that if the primitive Saints reaſon of not admitting unbaptized perſons to their communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be not our reaſon, or is not in being to us in relation to the godly Pedobaptiſts, then their practice cannot be our binding preſident, nor our literall variation, a morall violation of their order.</p>
                  <p>See we then whether the reaſon of the primitive Saints ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting onely baptized Diſciples to their communion, be a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to us to exclude the godly Pedobaptiſts, or rather whether it be not a binding reaſon to us why they ſhould be admitted to communion.</p>
                  <p>The reaſon of admitting ſuch and ſuch onely as they did to the communion of Saints, muſt needs be their appearance to be Saints: The ſaintly qualification of the perſon, muſt needs be the adequate reaſon of his admiſſion to Saints communion. When thoſe in Church-communion were ſtill ſtiled Saints in the inſcriptions of the Epiſtles ſent them, they received that denomination from that which was the ground and reaſon of their communion. See <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Phil:</hi> 1.1. <hi>Col:</hi> 1.1. The reaſon therefore why they admitted baptized and onely baptized to their communion in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, was becauſe they had reaſon to eſteem ſuch and onely ſuch for Saints. Any man that ſhould then have refuſed Baptiſme, (ſuppoſing no conſcientious ſcruple about it then in being among the Saints) it would have been and indeed was argument ſufficient againſt his Saintſhip or being a cordiall Diſciple of Chriſt. To deny Chriſt and to deny to be baptized in his name, was much the ſame thing then. Upon which ground the refuſing or not deſiring of Baptiſme in whomſoever found, was ground to the Saints then to refuſe or not deſire communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them. And as it was then, ſo it is now in like caſe:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41880:16"/>where the want of a regular Baptiſme now, is as much an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of no grace as it was in the primitive times, there it is as much an argument of non-communion with ſuch perſons now as then.</p>
                  <p>But where the want of any thing which belongs to a regular Baptiſme, is no argument of non-Saintſhip, there I think it can be no argument of non-communion with Saints. They having that upon which the communion of Saints is ſounded (to wit, Saintſhip) muſt needs have a right to the communion it ſelfe. If baptiſme in the primitive times was a reaſon ſubordinately of communion as it was an argument of Saintſhip, then by the rule of contraries, the want of it can be no argument againſt communion, but as ſuch a want is an argument of non-Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Of this more afterwards.</p>
                  <p>But moſt certain it is that the want of regular baptiſme, which is laid to the Pedobaptiſts charge, is no argument of non-Saintſhip in many of them; it proceeding not from want of a ſincere love to Chriſt; of which love many of them have given an ample teſtimony otherwiſe both in doing and ſuffering for him, but meerly from want of light in the thing; they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing (and I believe in good earneſt) that if they did not believe they were baptized already, it ſhould be one of the firſt things they would ſeeke opportunitie to doe, to become baptized. You ſee then upon what ground the primitive pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of holding communion with none but baptized Diſciples, is not binding to us but in like caſes.</p>
                  <p>But what ever the other was, to be ſure this was a Goſpel order among the primitive Saints, the morall reaſon whereof does as well oblige us as them; to wit, Saints holding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with ſuch in whom there was the appearance of Saints, notwithſtanding all ignorances, errings, and miſtakes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And why any or our brethren ſhould have their eye ſo much upon that other piece of Goſpel order, and overlooke this, and not thinke themſelves as much and much more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by this then that, eſpecially conſidering that there is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept upon precept as well as preſident in this caſe, but not ſo in the other, I am ſure I (not to ſay they) can give no good reaſon. But of this more afterward.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41880:17"/>
                  <head>Fifth Argument for Separation comes out thus.</head>
                  <p>If Baptiſme bear the ſame relation to the Supper of the Lord, as Circumciſion did to the Paſſeover, then no unbaptized per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be admitted to the Supper of the Lord, becauſe none uncircumciſed might be admitted to the Paſſeover.</p>
                  <p>But Baptiſme does bear the ſame relation to the Supper of the Lord as Circumciſion did to the Paſſeover. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall not inſiſt upon the undermining the baſis of this propoſition, by aſſerting that Circumciſion was not in all caſes abſolutely previouſly neceſſary to communion in the Paſſeover: as in the caſe of women, who were communicants in that ordinance though not circumciſed: and likewiſe in the caſe of neer forty yeares intermiſſion of Circumciſion in the wilderneſſe; in which time there was one Paſſeover, to be ſure, if not many more: for I have that which will be more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory then this.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall therefore deny the Minor propoſition: Baptiſme does not beare the ſame relation to the Lords Supper, as Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion did to the Paſſeover. That relation which Circumciſion did bear to the Paſſeover, as to make the former a neceſſary qualification in a perſon for the enjoyment of the latter, was the relation of an expreſſe command of God, making the one ſo neceſſary in relation to the other, as that the Lord did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly prohibit any uncircumciſed male to eat thereof, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. But now the New Teſtament affords us no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Law prohibiting communion in the Lords Supper to ſuch as upon any account are not baptized.</p>
                  <p>I doe acknowledge indeed that the New Teſtement does implicitly enjoyne Diſciples of Chriſt to be baptized before they participate in the Lords Supper; but not ſo as to make the latter act, to wit, communion in the Supper unlawfull without the former. Though Baptiſme be enjoyned to be received in its proper place and ſeaſon, yet all other after duties of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity are not forbidden in caſe the other ſhould unknowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or for want of a naturall or morall opportunity be deferred
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41880:17"/>or omitted. If a man omits one previous duty, as not knowing it to be his duty, or as thinking he hath already done it, when he hath not, it will not follow that he is hereupon bound to omit all other after duties which he knowes and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be his dutie. It is as much the duty of Pedobaptiſts to be baptized before the greateſt part of the prayers they make, the Chapters they read, the Sermons they hear, in order to their growth in grace already received, as it is for them to be baptized before they participate in the Supper; and yet who will ſay that it is a ſin for them to pray, to read, or to heare the word for ſuch an end? And if it be not a ſin for them to doe theſe duties for their growth; why ſhould it be their ſin to have communion in the Supper for the ſame end? ſince there is as much reaſon to lay aſide the one, as to forbear the other, upon the forementioned ground. If they doe ſin, their ſin lies not in doing that which they know to be their duty; but in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that which is, but is not knowne by them ſo to be. And if theſe duties be lawfull in them to doe as Chriſtians, can it reaſonably be thought unlawfull for us to joyne with them in them? May we not joyne with them and hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them in that which is lawfull (being men having the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) becauſe we may not have communion with them, or joyne with them in that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull? Or does our communion with them in that which is good, make us guilty of their infirmities or miſtakes, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they know that we diſallow them? If this were ſo, there would have been no roome for Chriſtian communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the weake and ſtrong Chriſtians in the Apoſtles dayes; the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b-eaters and the fleſh-eaters; thoſe that were for the obſerving of ſuch a day, and thoſe that were not: thoſe that were for circumciſing, and thoſe that were not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But was not Chriſt as faithfull in his houſe, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was in his? <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2. If ſo; hath not he been as pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticular and as ſtrict in his lawes for communion, as namely that no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized perſon ſhould taſt of his Supper, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the uncircumciſed to eat of the Paſſeover?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt is and hath been as faithfull in his houſe, as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41880:18"/>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> was in his; but how? not in deſcending to ſo many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities about externall ordinances as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring all that he had received from his father to make known, <hi>John</hi> 12.49, 50. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.15. As <hi>Moſes</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> faithfull to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his Commiſſion, ſo was Chriſt to the utmoſt latitude of his. But then it will follow, that if Chriſt hath no where given a law in like manner, and upon like termes, forbidding all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized Diſciples communion in the Supper, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did for the reſtraining of the uncircumciſed from the Paſſeover, that the reaſon is becauſe he had no ſuch command from his father, and conſequently that it is not the fathers will to lay the ſame reſtraint in the one caſe, as he did in the other. This I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, may be an anſwer fully ſati factory, to this fifth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>I might here have ſhewed, that the New Teſtament makes the Chriſtian Circumciſion, which conſiſts in the <hi>putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2.29. Phil. 3.3.</note> (Col: 2.11.) to anſwer more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to Circumciſion in the fleſh, then Baptiſme does; and conſequently that as the literall Circumciſion was the bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of communion in the old Teſtament Church, ſo the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Circumciſion is the boundary of communion in the New Teſtament Church: No men being to be knowne or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for Church-members now after the fleſh, as by Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion they were wont to be; but now, <hi>if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature:</hi> upon that account to be looked upon as one in Chriſt, (2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.16, 17.) As the want then of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Baptiſme is an argument that the new creatureſhip is wanting, ſo farre I ſhall grant the want of it an argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt communion with thoſe that want it, but no further as I ſee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>Sixth Argument for Separation, is to this effect.</head>
                  <p>If the practice of holding communion with ſuch onely as are baptized after faith, be more ſafe and more full of Scripture light and evidence, then the practice of holding communion with Pedobaptiſts is, then ſuch a practice is rather to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen then the other.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41880:18"/>
                  <p>But the practice of holding communion with ſuch onely as are baptized after faith, is more ſafe, and more full of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-light and evidence, then the other is: Therefore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here the Minor is again denyed: It is not more ſafe nor more full of Scripture-light and evidence to hold commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with ſuch onely as are baptized after faith, when in the doing of it, communion with other godly Chriſtians of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent perſwaſion, is rejected. There is no Scripture-light or evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for this, neither of precept or example, (as will be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhewed afterwards) but is a practice attended with dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and inconvenience both to themſelves and others, and to the affaires of Jeſus Chriſt now abroad in the world, as hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been ſhewed, and needs not here to be repeated, and will be further touched on afterward.</p>
                  <p>And this much ſhall ſuffice for the taking downe of the old building, which yet indeed was not old, but new. I ſhall now proceed to the erecting of that in its place and roome, which as I judge, will be more ſubſtantiall, beautifull, and ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, then the other was.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="arguments">
               <head>Six Arguments for the lawfulneſſe of Church-Communion, between the godly Pedobaptiſts and Anabaptiſts, notwithſtanding their different perſwaſion touching infant and after Baptiſm.</head>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>I. <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ALL thoſe that are viſibly of Chriſts univerſall body, have thereby a right to communion in particular Churches: but ſome which are for infant Baptiſme, are viſibly of Chriſts univerſall body: therefore ſome which are for infant baptiſme, have a right to communion in particular Churches.</p>
                  <p>Before I endeavour the proofe of the propoſition, take a word for explication of ſome of the termes of it.</p>
                  <p>By the univerſall body of Chriſt, I meane all thoſe that are actually united to him, and are thereby in an actuall and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41880:19"/>capacity of being ſaved by him. Thoſe in Scripture are called <hi>the body of Chriſt; his body the Church; the whole body;</hi> and <hi>the generall aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born,</hi> Eph: 4.12, 16. &amp; 1.22, 23. Col: 1.18, 24. Heb: 12.23. Of this number ſome are inviſible, and ſome viſible. Of thoſe that are inviſible, ſome are in the other world, and ſome in this. Thoſe in this world that are of Chriſts body, and yet not viſibly ſo, are ſuch as are united to Chriſt by internall grace, and have not yet had opportunity to manifeſt it by a ſuitable profeſſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. Thoſe are viſibly of this body, whoſe profeſſion and converſation is declarative of this ſpirituall union. And of this number are many of thoſe that are for infant baptiſme. Thus much for explication; now to our proofe of the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>It is affirmed in the Major propoſition, that all thoſe that are viſibly of Chriſts univerſall body, have thereby a right to communion in particular Churches.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The truth of this is obvious to common ſenſe; for what can be imagined to be ſo eſſentiall to communion, as union? In all bodyes whether naturall, myſticall, or politicall, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of parts flowes from union with the whole. Chriſt being the common head of Chriſtians, and center of union, hence it is that all that are united to him, are united one to another; or (according to the Apoſtles phraſe) <hi>are members one of another, Rom:</hi> 12.5. And being ſo, communion in giving and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mutuall help, is the naturall effect and common right of ſuch union. It would be monſterous in nature (and can it be otherwiſe in grace) for one member of the ſame body to deny the communication of comfort to the other: <hi>No man</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ever hated his owne fleſh, but nouriſheth and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth it, as the Lord doth the Church,</hi> Eph. 5.29. And does the Lord nouriſh and cheriſh ſuch becauſe they are his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers? and ſhall it be denied amongſt thoſe that are members one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> another? God forbid!</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Communion is the end of union, or that for the ſake of which union is made. Chriſt tooke our nature into union with himſelfe, that by communication he might become Wiſdome,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41880:19"/>Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption to us. And he hath <hi>knit together</hi> the ſeverall parts, that the whole body might increaſe and be edified <hi>by that which every joynt ſupplieth by the effectuall working of the meaſure of every part,</hi> Eph: 4.16. Col: 2.19. And therefore to deny communion to thoſe among whom there is union, is to croſſe and fruſtrate the very end of union.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That which is given and belongs to the whole body, is given and belongs to every part. But <hi>the work of miniſtration</hi> (as the word is rendred) to wit, of the ordinances of Chriſt, is ordained for the <hi>edification of the whole body,</hi> Eph: 4.12. and conſequently for every part. All that in common is given to the Church, (as the ordinances as well as other things are,) is given to every one that is Chriſts, as all thoſe are who are united to him, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.21, 22, 23. And the paſture that is provided for the ſheep of Chriſts flock, belongs to every one that by Chriſt enters into his owne ſheepfold, <hi>John</hi> 10.9. To conclude then; what better, ſtronger, or more rightfull claime, can any have to communion in a particular Church, then his memberſhip in the univerſall?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. Againſt this it may be ſome will object, that union with the Church does not give ſuch a right to communion in it, but that ſome unworthy and unchriſtian behaviour may be a juſt barr to ones communion with the Church, at ſuch time as his union with it, is not denyed. The Apoſtle commands to withdraw from every brother that walks diſorderly, not work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at all, but walking as a buſie-body; and yet during the time of this withdrawing, he would have ſuch an one to be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as a brother, and not counted as an enemy: and what is this leſſe then to acknowledge him as yet a brother in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Church, and yet to deny him communion in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſociety? 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3.6-15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> When ſuch ſcandalls in life or doctrine are found in a perſon that hath been owned for one of Chriſts Church, as does ſo farre contradict that chriſtian profeſſion by which he was firſt received into communion with the Church, as to give juſt ground of ſuſpition that there was never that internall uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41880:20"/>with Chriſt and his Church, which ſuch profeſſion did ſeem to import, or if there were, that it hath been ſince diſſolved by ſuch an offenſive walking, as is juſtly ſuſpected to be inconſiſtent with true grace: I ſay while things are in ſuch a doubtfull &amp; ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious poſture, and in a way of ripening for a finall judgment of the Church about his cutting off; ſuch a carriage of the Church towards ſuch a Delinquent, ſeemes moſt ſuitable, as by which he ſhall be declared neither clearly on, nor clearly off the Church, but hanging in ſuſpence; as namely by ſuſpending him communion as one going off the Church if not recovered, and yet to be admoniſhed as a brother not yet totally caſt off. And this ſeemes clearly to be the caſe of thoſe whom the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call rule in 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3.6-15 concernes. But then this will not be found of force againſt the admiſſion of ſuch godly Pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts to Church-communion, who hold their ſuppoſed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour upon ſuch termes, as does not at all render their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and internall union with Chriſt, &amp; ſo with his Church, juſtly ſuſpected in the account of ſober, impartiall, and judicious Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The diſorderly walking in 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3. contrary to the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Apoſtles, which was to be proceeded againſt by with-drawing from ſuch as were guilty of it, was not every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order that was contrary to Apoſtolical tradition or inſtitution, as is moſt evident. For the Apoſtles clearly taught ſuch meats might lawfully be eaten, which ſome ſcrupled, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 4.3, 4, 5. and likewiſe ſome dayes to be common, which ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did count ſacred, <hi>Col:</hi> 2.16, 17. <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.10, 11. and Circumciſion to be unneceſſary, which ſome Chriſtians thought neceſſary, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7.19. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.6. and yet for all that, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yea required the admiſſion of ſuch godly Chriſtians to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who meerly through weakneſſe and want of convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were found in theſe things diſorderly and non-obedient to thoſe Apoſtolicall traditions or inſtitutions, <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.1.-6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.1, 7. <hi>Acts</hi> 21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The diſorderly walking in 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3. to be proceeded againſt by withdrawing from ſuch as were guilty of it, was of a morall nature, and of publick ſcandall to thoſe without as well
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41880:20"/>as thoſe within the Church, and not matter of doubtfull diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation among good Chriſtians, as the other things were. For ſuch was, not working, and playing the buſie-bodyes, (1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 4.11, 12. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.13, 14. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.15.) which yet was the diſorder preciſely for which the Apoſtle enjoynes withdrawing from in 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3. Yea it was an evill of that nature, and ſo contradictious to the Chriſtian profeſſion, that according to the ſame Apoſtles own account, whoſoever made himſelfe guilty of it, denyed the faith, and rendred himſelfe worſe then an I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fidell, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.8. And therefore no marvell if not meet to be continued in communion, when the profeſſion and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, the only viſible witneſſe of internall union, is rendred invalid by ſo mighty a contradiction.</p>
                  <p>But what's this to the godly Pedobaptiſts caſe? whoſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed errour is not of a morall nature, nor of publick ſcandall to thoſe without, nor ſuch as does invalidate the teſtimony of their profeſſion and converſation, as witneſſing their internall union with Chriſt and his Church; nor ſo much as rendering it doubtfull, nor juſtly to be ſuſpected; but a matter of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſputation among many of thoſe that are truely godly, and not of leaſt diſcerning in ſpirituall affaires.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. It may be yet further objected; that though its true that memberſhip with Chriſt, and in the Church univerſall, gives a remote right to communion in particular Churches, yet none can have an immediate right without Baptiſme after faith, that being the door of enterance into the Church.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer; 1. That though its true that Baptiſme is neceſſary by way of duty to give a man an orderly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat right to particular Church-fellowſhip, when he hath an opportunity of being baptized, yet it will not therefore follow that its abſolutely neceſſary by way of means or under penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without which ſuch fellowſhip and communion is not to be had, when the reaſon of the want of ſuch Baptiſme, is the want of opportunity to enjoy it. The truth whereof appears by this undeniable reaſon: Baptiſme is no more neceſſary to Church-communion, then it is to ſalvation. For how can the means be more neceſſary to the ſubordinate, then it is to the principall
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41880:21"/>end? If Baptiſme be neceſſary to Church-communion, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Church-communion is reſpectively neceſſary to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for neither of them would be neceſſary, if no ſuch thing were as ſalvation is, to which they both relate. But now Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is neceſſary to ſalvation but by way of duty when oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity occurs, but is not neceſſary by way of means, ſo as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which ſalvation is not to be had, when opportunity of doing ones duty in this kinde is wanting. This is our conſtant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant doctrine, againſt the too much rigidity of Popiſh ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. And therefore if Baptiſme be neceſſary to ſalvation but upon ſuch termes, then ſurely it cannot be neceſſary to Church-communion upon higher or more ſtrict termes; if any thing may be remitted in the ſtrictneſſe of the termes of neceſſity, it would rather be as it relates to its leſſe principall then prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall end.</p>
                  <p>But now that the true reaſon why the godly Pedobaptiſts are not baptized after faith, is the want of a morall opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is a thing not to be doubted. For all the while they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine unconvinced that it is their duty, or ſo much as lawfull for them to be ſo baptized, ſo long they are clearly under the want of a morall opportunity of receiving ſuch a Baptiſme. For they can no more lawfully be ſo baptized during the time of ſuch diſſatisfaction, then others can who are ſatisfied, whilſt they want the opportunity of health, water, or a meet admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator.</p>
                  <p>It was as much the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> duty to be circumciſed before their admiſſion to communion in any part of congregationall worſhip, (the time preſcribed for Circumciſion conſidered) as it is the duty of believers to be baptized before admiſſion to Church communion, (yea the Law was more expreſſe in that poynt then the Goſpel is in this,) and yet for want of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of performing the one, the other was en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it for a certaine ſeaſon in the wilderneſſe. The want then of a morall opportunity of doing that which in order of nature ſhould goe before, is not a barr againſt the doing of all hat which according to common order ſhould follow after; for then it would as well be unlawfull for the godly Pedobaptiſts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41880:21"/>to proceed in a long continued courſe of hearing, praying, &amp;c. for their edification in the grace they have received, as it would be for them to breake bread in remembrance of the Lords death; becauſe their baptiſme after faith, ought as well to precede the one as the other. But ſurely it is not in the heart of any tender Chriſtian, to ſuſpend them the exerciſe of theſe, untill they are ſatisfied touching the other. And I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by what law or rule they come under ſuſpenſion any more in the one, then in the other? Their ſuppoſed ſin, then, lies not in this; that they breake bread and performe other Chriſtian duties before they are baptized; but in this, that they omit Baptiſme after the proper ſeaſon of it. And it does not follow that communion may not be held with them in that which is lawfull, yea their duty, becauſe it may not be held with them in that which is their ſuppoſed weakneſſe in omitting a duty: a conſent in the one, and a declared diſapprobation of the other, may well conſiſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To the objection which ſuppoſeth internall union with the Church, to give only a remote right to Church-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but Baptiſme the immediate right, I further anſwer thus; Baptiſme does not of it ſelfe conſtitute a right to Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but is declarative of that which does: it is the union by grace which conſtitutes a mans right when made viſible, and not Baptiſme otherwiſe then as it is declarative of this. That this is ſo, appeares thus: When ſuch a hereſie or ſcandalous life does occurre a man that hath been baptized, as does totally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the grace of union, or declare the non-being of it; his Baptiſme cannot protect him from being cut off communion with the Church, as it would doe, if of it ſelfe it did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a mans right. And is there not the ſame reaſon why the involuntary want of regular Baptiſme ſhould not deprive a man of communion, if the grace of union which does conſtitute his right to it be apparently viſible otherwiſe? If baptiſme cannot give a man right in the abſence of viſible grace; why ſhould the involuntary want of it deprive him of it in the preſence of viſible grace?</p>
                  <p>It is true, Baptiſme is reputed the doore of enterance into
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41880:22"/>the Church: and the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>by one Spirit, we are all baptized into o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e body,</hi> 1 Cor: 12.13. But how? Surely not by originall conſtitution, but by way of ſigne and ſolemnizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Which agrees to the nature and uſuall deſcription of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, as they are called, as conſiſting of outward ſigne, and inward grace: the letter of the ordinance as to this uſe of it, being but the ſigne of the ſpirituall union and communion which by it is profeſſedly declared to be between him that is baptized, and the reſt of Chriſts body. So that mens actuall, reall, and ſpirituall union and memberſhip with Chriſt, and ſo with the Church (which is the ground of communion) is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and ought to precede the ſolemnization of it by way of ſigne. The ſigne, to wit, Baptiſme with water, delivers the baptized into the viſible union and communion of the Church, by pointing to and declaring their inward and ſpirituall union and communion with it, as that which gives them right to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and viſible communion. If then the grace of ſpirituall union which fundamentally gives a man right to Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, may be evidenced and declared by other means with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regular Baptiſme, (though its every Chriſtians duty to have his baptiſme concurre in ſuch declaration, when he hath oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſo to doe,) it will not follow then, that the want of ſuch baptiſme betiding a man through unavoydable neceſſity in the want of opportunity, will deprive him of an immediate right to ſuch communion. But that the grace of ſpirituall union which many that are for infant baptiſme, have with Chriſt the head, and his body the Church, is clearly evidenced, though they not baptized after faith, is that which in the next place I am to undertake the proofe of.</p>
                  <p>My Minor propoſition then, was this: But ſome which are for infant baptiſme, are viſibly of Chriſts univerſall body: which I prove thus.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If thoſe eſſentiall and conſtitutive properties and marks, by which the viſible members of the primitive Churches which were of Chriſts univerſall body, were deſcribed and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from thoſe that were not, are viſibly in ſome that are for infant baptiſme, then ſome that are for infant baptiſme,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41880:22"/>are viſibly of Chriſts univerſall body.</p>
                  <p>But thoſe eſſentiall and conſtitutive properties and markes by which the viſible members of the primitive Churches that were of Chriſts univerſall body, were deſcribed and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, are viſible in ſome that are for infant baptiſme. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe the conſequence of the Major propoſition, will not be denyed, <hi>viz.</hi> that if the ſame things which eſſentially made the ſound members of the primitive Churches to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly of the univerſall body of Chriſt, be found in Pedobaptiſts, that then there is all reaſon to conclude them to be of the ſame body, what ever defects otherwiſe may be found in them. For thoſe properties and formall differences which are argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative and declarative of the kinde, doe argue and declare all to be of that kinde, in whom thoſe properties and formall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences are found. If a humane body and reaſonable ſoule be eſſentiall to mankinde, and that by which that kinde of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth formally differ from all other; then it muſt needs follow that all that have a humane body and reaſonable ſoule, (what ever other defects in nature they have,) are of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</p>
                  <p>For the examination of the truth of the Minor; we will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what thoſe eſſentiall and conſtitutive properties and marks were, by which thoſe of the primitive Churches were diſcerned to be of Chriſts univerſall body, and diſtinguiſhed from thoſe that were not: and then conſider whether the ſame things, properties and marks, be not viſible in many that are for infant baptiſme. Thoſe that were of Chriſts body in <hi>Rome,</hi> you have diſtinguiſhed from the reſt in <hi>Rome</hi> that were not, by this propertie; <hi>called to be Saints,</hi> Rom: 1.7. Thoſe in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> in like manner by theſe; <hi>Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints:</hi> and others of the ſame body elſe-where, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by this, that they are ſuch <hi>as call upon the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, both theirs and ours;</hi> to wit, believingly, and ſincerely, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.2. Thoſe of the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> thus: <hi>The Saints which are at Epheſus, the faithfull in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Eph: 1.1. Thoſe at <hi>Philippi,</hi> thus; <hi>All the Saints
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41880:23"/>in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phii: 1.1. Thoſe at <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> thus: <hi>The Saints and faithfull brethren in Chriſt,</hi> Col: 1.2.</p>
                  <p>Now that there are many of thoſe that are for infant bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, concerning whom it is meet for us and for all Saints to think, that they are <hi>called to be Saints; ſanctified in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> are <hi>faithfull in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> are faithfull brethren in Chriſt; and ſuch as call (and that in faith) upon the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, both theirs and ours, I hope no ſober Chriſtian will deny: and to thinke otherwiſe would argue lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle skill in Chriſtianity, and an extraordinary deep poverty in charity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I further prove that ſome that are for infant baptiſme, are of the univerſall body of Chriſt, thus. All that doe truely believe in Jeſus Chriſt, are members of that univerſall body whereof he is the head: but ſome for infant baptiſme doe ſo believe, <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c. The Minor needs no proof. The Major, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſo many of thoſe that are for infant baptiſme as doe unfeignedly believe in Jeſus Chriſt, are members of his body; or which is the ſame, are of his Church, I prove from <hi>Heb:</hi> 3.6. <hi>But Chriſt as a Son over his owne houſe: whoſe houſe are we, if we hold faſt the confidence, and the rejoycing of the hope firme unto the end.</hi> Againe, <hi>ver:</hi> 14. <hi>For we are made partakers of Chriſt, if we hold the beginning of our confidence ſtedfaſt unto the end.</hi> It was their faith and confidence in Chriſt (we ſee) that made them partakers of Chriſt, and to be of his houſe which is the Church, (1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.15.) and upon their perſeverance in this confidence, did depend their perſeverance in this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And the ſame faith which did make them partakers of Chriſt, and to be of his houſe, when found in thoſe that are for infant baptiſme, will produce the ſame effect, and procure them the ſame priviledge. The Saints are called the <hi>houſhold of faith,</hi> (Gal: 6.10.) as receiving that denomination from their faith which makes them of Gods houſe. <hi>They are all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that have faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. and ſuch as are Sons, <hi>abide in Gods houſe for ever,</hi> as members of his family, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.35. For God hath no children that are not of his houſhold.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41880:23"/>
                  <p n="3">3. If ſome that are for infant baptiſme are <hi>reconciled to God</hi> by Chriſts death on the croſſe, upon their believing, and ſo through Chriſt, and <hi>by the Spirit, have an acceſſe unto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> then ſuch <hi>are no more ſtrangers and forrainers, but fellow-Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God,</hi> Epheſ: 2.16-19.</p>
                  <p>But ſome that are for infant baptiſme, are ſo reconciled, and have ſuch an acceſſe to the father: This is not without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Antipedobaptiſts, and therefore needs no farther proofe. Therefore we may well conclude, that ſome that are for infant baptiſme, are no more ſtrangers and forreiners, but fellow-citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Againſt the pertinency of the forecited proofes to conclude Pedobaptiſts to be viſibly of the body of Chriſt, it may perhaps be objected; that all thoſe Chriſtians of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Churches, of which the forecited Scriptures make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were all baptized after the profeſſion of faith; and that it will not follow, that becauſe faith, ſanctification, and the reſt of thoſe qualifications, did denominate ſuch as were baptized after faith, to be of the Church, that therefore they muſt deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate ſuch as are not baptized after faith, to be of the Church likewiſe. For as they had one faith, ſo they had one baptiſme (<hi>Eph:</hi> 4.5.) and this did beare its ſhare in their Chriſtian denomination and diſtinction, as well as any other qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer. That it was the faith, calling, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication as ſuch, and the viſibility of theſe, by which thoſe Chriſtians were deſcribed and denominated to be of the Church, and diſtinguiſhed from thoſe that were not; and therefore thoſe that are under the ſame qualifications eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally (as ſome Pedobaptiſts are,) though perhaps not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially, muſt needs come under the ſame denomination of memberſhip in the Church of Chriſt If the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> were now alive, and ſhould write an Epiſtle to the Church of God in <hi>London,</hi> inſcribing and directing it to all in <hi>London</hi> that are called to be Saints; or ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus; or the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Chriſt; would it not be reaſonable to think that all ſuch
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41880:24"/>Pedobaptiſts there, as are called to be Saints, and ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus; were hereby meant as well as thoſe that are ſuch among thoſe that have been baptized after profeſſion of faith?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The moſt that I think can rationally be ſaid, is, that the Baptiſme of thoſe Chriſtians in the primitive Churches, did beare it; ſhare, and was one ingredient in denominating them perſons called to be Saints, ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but not that it did wholly or mainly conſtitute it. Not but that the faith, calling, and ſanctification of many Pedobaptiſts is the ſame in the maine, with thoſe primitive Saints, (they are <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of like precious faith,</hi> 2 Pet: 1.1.) only it hath not, it may be, all the ſame ingredients in it to make it altogether ſo compleat and rich as theirs was. So that if this defect, and the want of this ingredient of regular baptiſme, do not nullifie the viſibility of the faith, calling, and ſanctification of the Pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, then they may truely be ſaid to have the ſame faith, calling, and ſanctification in kinde, if not in degree, which the primitive Saints had. Baptiſme doth not conſtitute another kinde of faith and Saintſhip then the ſame perſons had before they were baptized; all that can be ſuppoſed, is, that it tends towards the compleating of theſe in degrees of being and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And yet I doubt not but that taking one thing with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, compariſon may be made between the viſibility of Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as it was in ſome at leaſt of thoſe primitive Saints, and as it now is in many that are for infant baptiſme, and that in point of degree. If the viſibility of Saintſhip in Pedobaptiſts, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective for want of regular baptiſme; may we not well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the viſibility of the ſanctification of ſome primitive Church-members that were owned as brethren in Chriſt, was defective much more on another ſcore? Weigh &amp; conſider the erronious opinions, ſuperſtitious cuſtoms, uncharitable contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; cenſurings, and other too much ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uall deportment, that was yet remaining and found among thoſe that were owned for brethren; viſible Saints, and members of the primitive Church; and then let conſcience judge, whether in the whole; advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41880:24"/>and diſadvantages compared in both, the Chriſtian viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and ſanctification of very many Pedobaptiſts, doe not ſhine much brighter, and give a far more diſtinct and indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table teſtimony of their ſpirituall and internall memberſhip with Chriſt and his Church, then many of the others did. See 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.7. with 10.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.5. <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.1, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.18, 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Argument</hi> II.</head>
                  <p>ALL thoſe whom the Lord now in times of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament hath received into communion with himſelfe, thoſe his children ought to receive to communion with them.</p>
                  <p>But ſome that are for infant Baptiſme are ſuch whom the Lord hath received into communion with himſelfe. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>That the Lords receiving perſons to communion with him, is now under the New Teſtament a ſufficient reaſon why his children ſhould receive the ſame to communion with them, I conceive is ſufficiently evident by theſe Scriptures. <hi>Rom:</hi> 15.7. <hi>Wherefore receive ye one another, as Chriſt alſo received us, to the glory of God.</hi> And againe, <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.1, 3. <hi>Him that is weake in the faith receive you. Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him that eateth not: and let not him that eateth not, judge him that eateth: [for God hath received him.]</hi> The caſe was this: Some of the believing Jewes and Gentiles ſtood at too great a diſtance by reaſon of their different perſwaſion touching ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things. That by which the Apoſtle would convince them of their errour herein, and ſo bring them to cloſe communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is by laying before them the diſſimilitude that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lords carriage and theirs towards the ſame perſons, and the conformity and agreement that ought to be. That they did not receive thoſe whom the Lord had received, was their fault, but to receive ſuch as he had received, was their dutie. The Apoſtles Argument is built upon this ſuppoſition: that the Lord is a pattern unto his people in receiving perſons to communion: and if caſt into forme, would be this. Thoſe whom the Lord receives to communion, his people ought to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41880:25"/>receive to communion too: but the Lord receives both Jewes and Gentiles, weake and ſtrong Chriſtians, notwithſtanding their different perſwaſions, therefore you his people ought to doe ſo too. See the connexion of <hi>Rom:</hi> 15.7, 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Theſe differing Saints who are thus en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyned by the Apoſtle to receive one another, notwithſtanding their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, were all baptized perſons, and therefore that by which they were obliged to receive one another, can be no rule for ſuch as are baptized, to receive ſuch as are unbaptized, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe they were all baptized; yet their receiving one another is not urged from their baptiſme, but from the Lords receiving them. Their baptiſme here, was no further an argument why they ſhould receive one another, then as it was an argument that the Lord had received them. And by the ſame reaſon, on the contrary, no errour about Baptiſme can be a reaſon why ſuch erronious perſons ſhould not be received, further then it is an argument that the Lord hath not received them: The Lords receiving or not receiving perſons, muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate his people in their receiving and refuſing to receive them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Theſe differing Saints were all in communion of the Church already; and therefore their receiving one another to which they are exhorted, cannot import their receiving one another ſimply to communion, but onely a receiving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to a neerer and cloſer communion: how then can this be a ground for thoſe that are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Church-communion together at all, to receive one another to ſuch communion?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very well, though that which is ſuppoſed in the objection, ſhould be granted. For that which is a ground of a further degree of communion, muſt needs be a ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſimply conſidered: a further degree alwayes includes and ſuppoſes the firſt. If it be lawfull for me to goe with one two miles, it cannot be unlawfull for me to goe with him one.</p>
                  <p>Againe, Conſider <hi>Acts</hi> 15.8, 9. for further proofe of my propoſition; <hi>And God which knoweth the hearts, bare them wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41880:25"/>giving them the holy Ghoſt, even as he did unto us: and put no difference between us and them, purifying their hearts by faith.</hi> The queſtion was this; Whether it were needfull to circumciſe the believing Gentiles; a thing which ſome belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jewes impoſed as neceſſary, not only to their owning them as brethren in communion, but alſo to ſalvation, <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 5. That by which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> would evince the contrary, is this: that God put no difference between them. If God made no difference between the uncircumciſed and circumciſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, then they ought not among themſelves: but God made none, but exhibited an equall teſtimony of reſpect to both, in giving the holy Ghoſt alike to both.</p>
                  <p>It is true the compariſon in outward form is not alike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the baptized and not baptized after faith, as is between the circumciſed &amp; uncircumciſed believers: but yet there is the like reaſon why they ſhould make no more difference among themſelves, as to their owning one another as chriſtian brethren, then was to be made among the circumciſed and uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed believers. For if Gods purifying their hearts alike by faith, &amp; his giving them his Spirit alike, was concluſive againſt their diſowning one another as brethren upon account of their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences then in being; then the like equall diſtribution of Gods grace and Spirit to perſons that are not, as well as to thoſe that are baptized after faith, is concluſive too againſt alike diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another upon account of other differences now in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I pray you let it be noted that the Apoſtles argument for reconciliation, is not fetched from the nature of the things wherein they differed; but from the tenor of Gods carriage towards them that did differ, in giving them an equall intereſt in his grace, no withſtanding their difference: which in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt be of the ſame force to the ſame end now, to wit, the reconciliation of differing godly parties, though their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are not the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Of much what like import is that alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 11.17. <hi>For as much then as God gave them the like gift, as he did unto us who believed on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, what was I that I could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand God?</hi> Theſe words are uſed as an argument to juſtifie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41880:26"/>the Apoſtle <hi>Peters</hi> going into, and eating with the Gentiles: an action which otherwiſe was deemed as irregular, as the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of godly Pedobaptiſts to communion can be ſuppoſed to be, and at which ſome of the circumciſion, though believers, were at firſt offended, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.2. His argument conſtructively, ſeemes to be this; That if after God had given them an equall ſhare in his love with other believers of the circumciſion, teſtified by giving them the like gift of his grace and Spirit, (if after this) he ſhould have continued the wonted difference in his carriage towards Jewes and Gentiles, he ſhould have withſtood God who now made no difference, but ſhewed the ſame favour to the one as to the other. To keep at a diſtance then from thoſe to whom God drawes nigh in his ſpeciall favour and gifts of his grace and holy Spirit, is to ſteer a courſe contrary to God; or a practice by which thoſe that are guilty of it withſtand God. Is not this cleerly the doctrine of this text? And if ſo, what ſhall we then think of thoſe ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that abound in our dayes of Godly men from Godly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of particular differences, when God in the mean time is alike nigh to both in his ſpeciall and gracious communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and holds communion with both? Is this to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of God as dear children? <hi>Eph:</hi> 5.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But the caſe of admitting Pedobaptiſts to communion, is not the ſame with <hi>Peters</hi> going into and eating with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; and therefore the lawfulneſſe of the one, cannot be infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the lawfulneſſe of the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> No more was the not muzzling the mouth of the Ox which trode out the Corne, the ſame with maintaining the Elders that rule well and labour in the word and doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.17, 18. Nor was the Diſciples plucking the eares of Corne on the Sabbath day, the ſame with <hi>Davids</hi> eating of the Shew-bread, and the Prieſts ſlaying of ſacrifice on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>Math:</hi> 12.3, 4, 5. and yet the generall equity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity of the things compared, made the legality of the one practice argumentative of the legality of the other. And ſo I ſay in theſe two caſes of <hi>Peters</hi> going into the Gentiles, and of admitting Pedobaptiſts to communion; though in other things
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41880:26"/>they differ, yet in this they agree, <hi>viz.</hi> in that <hi>Peters</hi> action had been as much ſcrupled by him (<hi>Acts</hi> 10.28.) as this way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is by ſome; and likewiſe in that there is a like equall ſhare of ſpeciall grace vouchſafed by God to the differing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties now, as well as was then. And therefore why ſhould not this conſideration, ſerve to ſatisfie this doubt, and remove this ſcruple of ours, as well as it did theirs; and to cauſe us with <hi>Peter</hi> to think, that under ſuch circumſtances, a maintaining our former diſtance in this caſe, would be a withſtanding of God who hath taught us to doe otherwiſe, by his example of vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing equall communion to both. Gods equall diſtribution of ſpeciall grace to parties that differ, ſeemes to be ſo good a ground of communion one with another, as ſwallows up and beares downe, all leſſer differences that ſtand in the way.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>III. <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF Church-communion between the Godly Pedobaptiſts and Anabaptiſts, be more for common edification, their differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence notwithſtanding, then their ſeparation upon account of their difference can be; Then their communion is to be choſen before ſeparation, their difference notwithſtanding.</p>
                  <p>But the communion of ſuch is more for their edification then their ſeparation would be.</p>
                  <p>The reaſon of the conſequence why communion is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before ſeparation, where common edification is better provided for by it then by ſeparation, is taken from the end of ordinances, and Church-order, and communion in theſe; which is edification. Edification is that for the ſake of which the work of the miniſtery (which conſiſts in the miniſtration of word, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, diſcipline &amp; order) is given and ordained, <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.11, 12. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.10. And edification is the marke at which all Church-tranſactions are to aim, and to which to be levelled, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.26. <hi>Let all things be done to edifying.</hi> And the management of theſe holy things themſelves, muſt be regulated by their end, edification, to which they are ſubſervient; to be uſed, or their uſe ſuſpended; to be ſtrained
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41880:27"/>higher or lower, ſo as edification may beſt be provided for, <hi>Mat:</hi> 9.14-17. <hi>Mark</hi> 4.33. <hi>John</hi> 16.12. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.1, 2. Reaſon and Scripture teach us ſtill to ſubject the means unto the end: and is not the contrary prepoſterous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The holy reſt of the Sabbath in a ceſation from ſervile worke and bodily la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, was an ordinance of God: and yet when a ſtrict obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ordinance in the letter of it in ſuch a ceſation, did croſſe but one end of it, which was the bodily reſt and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch as were to keep it, (<hi>Exod:</hi> 23.12. <hi>Deut:</hi> 5.14.) then ſuch an obſervation of it, might lawfully be waved, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts doctrine in the caſe, as I underſtand it <hi>Mark</hi> 2.25, 26, 27. Spirituall gifts alſo, and in particular that of tongues, were given for the ſame generall end as the ordinances themſelves are, to wit, profit and edification, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.7, 10. And yet when the uſe of this gift by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in the caſe, was rendered unuſefull as to its end, <hi>viz.</hi> edification; the ſuſpention of its exerciſe was injoyned, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.5, 28. So though regular Baptiſme, according to ones opinion in the caſe, ought indeed to be inſiſted on as pre-requiſite to communion, where common edification among the godly may be accommodated and not hindered thereby: yet where a ſevere inſiſting on ſuch a regular Baptiſme in order to communion, ſhall croſſe edification by drawing on ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of godly from godly, why ſhould not ſuch ſeverity there be waved?</p>
                  <p>Touching the Minor propoſition, to wit, that Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion between ſuch differing Saints as aforeſaid, does tend more to their edification then their ſeparation can doe, is eaſie to apprehend, upon a double account.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe union and communion between Saints and Saints, gives them an opportunity of a free and full trade in their gifts and graces, by which they grow ſpiritually rich. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well doth the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tle make the increaſe of the body to the edifying of it ſelfe in love, to depend upon the <hi>joyning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the parts,</hi> and the ſupply of <hi>every joynt,</hi> and the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall working of the meaſure of <hi>every part,</hi> Eph: 4.16. Whereas on the contrary, diſtance and ſeparation, deprives
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41880:27"/>them of that ſpirituall commerce, and ſo tends to their impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhing. Juſt as it is between Country and Country; when differences breake out that obſtruct their wonted trade, they grow poor upon it. Or as it is with the naturall body, which weakens, waſts and conſumes, when the nutrimentall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe between part and part is obſtructed. And the ſad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes among profeſſors ſince their many differences in opinion have multiplied their ſeparations, doth wofully experience the truth hereof. How many are fallen, and are dead upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count? and how many more are ſick and ready to die? and ſhall we then for all this proceed on in ſo impoveriſhing and deſtructive a courſe!</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Communion increaſeth love, and love edifies, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.1. It edifies actively by inclining and diſpoſing men willingly and cheerfully to lay out themſelves in ſuch ſervices by which their brethren may be edified and comforted; according to that counſell, <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.13. <hi>By love ſerve one another.</hi> And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by enabling them for edification ſake to bear burdens; that is, the infirmities and miſtakes of brethren, which are a burden, as is enjoyned <hi>Rom:</hi> 15.1, 2. For <hi>charity beareth all things, indureth all things,</hi> 1 Cor: 13.7. It edifieth paſſively too, by rendering the chriſtian applications of brethren, and acts of ſervice, the more acceptable, and ſo the more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; taking all in the beſt part: <hi>It thinketh no evill, but believeth all things, hopeth all things, and rejoyceth in the truth,</hi> 1 Cor: 13.6, 7. But ſeparation breeds alienation and diminution of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, more or leſſe, and ſo weakens endeavours of edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and turnes them into ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her channell. For to what degree the ſpring of motion growes weake, to that degree motion it ſelfe will be ſlow. And to what degree love decreaſeth, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, jealouſies, and evill ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>miſes, will increaſe: and theſe diſpoſe perſons to ſuck poiſon from the ſweeteſt flower: and poiſon will not nouriſh. Therefore ſeparation of Saints from Saints, upon account of differences, is againſt edification.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ect.</hi> But <hi>can two walk together except they are agreed?</hi> their different opinions and different practiſes, will occaſion cotentions, and thoſe contentions will hinder edification and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41880:28"/>comfort: and therefore communion on ſuch termes, may be as much and more againſt edification, then ſeparation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have ſometimes thought ſo indeed. But</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Two that are agreed in the moſt and greateſt matters, may and ought to walke together, though in ſome fewer and leſſer things they diſagree. <hi>Whereto we have already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, let us walke by the ſame rule, let us minde the ſame thing,</hi> with humble expectation concerning ſuch that <hi>in any thing are otherwiſe minded, that God ſhall reveale even this unto them, Phil:</hi> 3.15, 16. The 14 and 15 Chap: <hi>Rom:</hi> is cleare for this.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whereas its ſaid thoſe differences will occaſion conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thoſe contentions will hinder edification and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: That they may doe ſo through mens weakneſſe, I grant, but that they muſt neceſſarily ſo doe I deny, and doe affirme that when ever ſuch contentions doe ariſe between the godly, as doe hinder edification; it is from want of wiſdome, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and moderation, in one or both parties: and to what is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, is no more an argument againſt the communion we ſpeak of, then mens inſidence to infirmities and fleſhly mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in prayer, or any other holy-duty, is an argument againſt the uſe of the duty it ſelfe. It is true, the difference among the Chriſtians at <hi>Rome,</hi> did oocaſion through intemperate zeal, carnall contentions, deſpiſings and judgings one of another, but it was their ſin and ſhame that they did ſo, and that for which they were juſtly blamed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom:</hi> 14. Such unchriſtian diſtempers muſt be mortified, not indulged; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt, and not improved againſt a duty: for that would be but to juſtifie one fault by another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But for thoſe that cannot hold Church-communion in breaking of bread with thoſe that are not baptized after faith, yet if they can hold an occaſionall communion with them in gifts and graces, in the word, prayer and conference, ſhall they not hereby ſufficiently free themſelves from the blame of hindering edification by their ſeparation?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Its confeſſed that thoſe that goe thus farre, have offered faire towards the demoliſhing of the wall of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41880:28"/>and ſo of freeing themſelves of the evils occaſioned by its ſtanding.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But though ſuch a partiall ſeparation as this, is not ſo much an enemy to edification as a totall one is, yet if ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of godly from godly in the ſimple nature of it be a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hinderance of edification, (and whether it be nor, judge by what's ſaid in my argument) then every degree of ſuch ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, muſt to a degree be guilty of the ſame evil. Without all doubt this partiall ſeparation, is to a degree a hinderance to charity, and conſequently to the ſame degree a hinderance of edification. Though there may be much love between parties that come ſo neer together as to hold communion in gifts and graces, yet queſtionleſſe there would be yet more, if that which keepes them as yet at ſome diſtance, were alſo removed. Its well worthy conſideration, that the <hi>Law of Commandements contained in ordinances,</hi> which were the wall of ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Jewes and Gentiles, are by the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.15. ſtiled the <hi>[enmity]</hi> and the breaking downe of this wall, the <hi>aboliſhing the enmity.</hi> And how were they the enmity? but as they were a means of ſeparation; for ſo they were an occaſion of enmity between thoſe people. And does not this clearely let us ſee, that ſeparation as ſuch, is attended with enmity, more or leſſe?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Me thinks that which ſatisfies them to hold communion in gifts and graces, word and prayer, with their differing bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, would lead them to ſatisfaction about the lawfulneſſe of communion with them in breaking of bread alſo, if they would but follow it. For doe they not by joyning in prayer with them, and ſaying our father which art in heaven, plainly acknowledge them to be children of the ſame father, and ſo their holy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: and if children of God, then believers in Chriſt, by which beliefe they are made the children of God: and if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in Chriſt, then members of Chriſt; and if members of Chriſt, then of his body the Church; and if of Chriſts body, then that they have communion with him in his fleſh, &amp; blood, and Spirit, and what can they acknoweldge that amounts to more then this, by having communion with them in the Lords
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41880:29"/>Supper? Or have they any example or direction in Scripture to joyne with them in prayer, with whom they may not joyne in breaking of bread?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>IV <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF ſeparation of Saints from Saints upon any account of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that does not unſaint them, or render their Saintſhip juſtly ſuſpected, be voyd of Scripture-precept, and of approved Scripture-preſident, Then the godly Anabaptiſts and godly Pedobaptiſts, need not ſeparate one from another upon account of their difference about Baptiſme, (for all conſcience of duty, ariſes from precept or preſident.)</p>
                  <p>But ſeparation of Saints from Saints upon any account of difference that does not unſaint them, or render their Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip juſtly ſuſpected, is voyd of Scripture-precept and of approved Scripture-preſident. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That ſuch ſeparation is voyd of Scripture-precept and of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Scripture-preſident, I take for granted, till the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary doe appeare, which I never expect. We read of many differences both of opinion and practice, and of diviſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, that were [in] the primitive Churches; but of no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved ſeparations [from] thoſe Churches upon account of thoſe differences. There were indeed that did forſake the Saints aſſemblies upon a carnall account, <hi>Heb:</hi> 10.25. that <hi>went out from them, becauſe they were not of them,</hi> 1 Joh: 2.19. but they were ſenſuall, not having the Spirit, <hi>Jude</hi> 19. There were others not ſo bad that did not proceed ſo farre, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of difference ſtood at ſome diſtance one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but how were they diſallowed and blamed for ſo doing? <hi>Acts</hi> 15. <hi>Rom:</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p>What is wont to be alledged for Scripture-precept in the caſe; I take to be impertinent, and to fall ſhort in proofe of what its brought for. That's one in <hi>Rom:</hi> 16.17. <hi>Mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoyd them.</hi> 1. Theſe were not Saints which they were to avoyd, but ſuch as <hi>ſerved not the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41880:29"/>but their owne bellies,</hi> ver. 18. 2. The diviſions and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences cauſed by them, for the ſake of which they were to be avoyded, were not about leſſer matters, or ſuch offences as would conſiſt with Saintſhip; for it was ſo farre from being a duty to avoyd one another upon that account, as that it was their ſin for which they were blamed when they did ſo, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. Or 3. if they were diviſions and offences about leſſer matters, for cauſing of which they were to be avoyded; then they were not to be avoyded for cauſing ſuch diviſions ſimply, (for ſo the Saints did which were to be received, <hi>Rom:</hi> 14.) but for cauſing them out of a carnall deſigne to ſerve their own bellies.</p>
                  <p>Another is, 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 3.6. <hi>Withdraw from every brother that walkes diſorderly,</hi> &amp;c. But to this I have ſpoken already in my firſt Argument, to which I referre you.</p>
                  <p>A third Scripture alledged for ſeparation, is, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.17. <hi>Wherefore come out from among them,</hi> &amp;c. But this does not call Saints from Saints, but Saints from infidell Idolaters, as <hi>ver:</hi> 14, 15, 16. With whom ſome of that Church had communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in eating of their Idol-ſacrifices in their Idols Temple, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8.7, 10.</p>
                  <p>But that Scripture on which I finde ſome to lay the greateſt ſtreſſe, is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> From which they argue, that God hath of his people in Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Babylon,</hi> to wit, <hi>Rome;</hi> and that having hereby given a call to them all to come out of her, if ſome will not at firſt obey the call but ſtay behinde, the reſt that underſtand it, and have a mind to obey it, muſt leave them behinde and ſeparate from them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To which firſt I might ſay, the paſſage doth not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſuppoſe that God hath in <hi>Babylon</hi> a people that are by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion actually his in Covenant, but a people that in obeying his call ſhall become ſuch. As when the Lord ſaid to <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 18.9, 10. <hi>Be not afraid but ſpeake, and hold not thy peace: for I am with thee, and no man ſhall ſet on thee to hurt thee: [for I have much people in this City.]</hi> His much people, were not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41880:30"/>thoſe that did already believe, at leaſt not all of them ſuch, but ſuch whom the Lord knew ſhould believe upon his conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing to preach the Goſpel there. In like manner when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 10.16. <hi>Other ſheep I have, which are not of this fold, them alſo I muſt bring, and they ſhall hear my voyce.</hi> The ſaying of Chriſt doth not import that thoſe other ſheep which he calls his, were then his by calling when he ſpake thoſe words, but were afterwards to become his, when he ſhould bring them to heare his voyce.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or ſecondly, if the words doe import a people that are Gods by call and covenant, that live in <hi>Babylon,</hi> then <hi>come out of her my people,</hi> &amp;c. may import Gods call to them for a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call remove, though in no actuall communion with her, partly to avoyd the temptations of ſo wicked a place, noted in thoſe words; <hi>that ye be not partakers of her ſins:</hi> and partly to eſcape her Judgements, noted in thoſe words; <hi>that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> As God ſometimes called <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and his people out of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at the approach of ruine to thoſe Cities. And then the words will no more imply a Church-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, then it would do for a man that lives in <hi>Paris</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to <hi>London,</hi> for better opportunities of grace, as the late converted <hi>Turk</hi> did.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But thirdly, ſuppoſe the words to be underſtood of ſuch as are actually Gods people, even then while as yet they are in ſuperſtitious communion with ſuch Idolaters or others in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> as are none of Gods people by Goſpel call and Covenant grace; yet this would be no ground for to withdraw from or deny communion with a Congregation of godly Pedobaptiſts that are ſeparated in their communion from the ungodly of the world, (which is our caſe) becauſe the caſe between the other and them wholly differs.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For firſt if there ſhould be any in the aſſemblies of the <hi>Romane Babylon,</hi> that in the midſt of ſo much wood, hay and ſtubble of errour and ſuperſtition, ſhould have ſo much of the gold, ſilver, and precious ſtones of ſound doctrine, right faith, and true grace, as would denominate them Gods people, yet theſe are in their Church-worſhip, involved among perſons
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41880:30"/>that are in ſome of their tenents hereticall, in their worſhip idolatrous, and in their converſations openly profane. Which are ſuch cauſes of non-communion, as are not to be found in the well reformed Congregations of godly Pedobaptiſts, whether Presbyteriall, or Independent. And therefore where there is not the ſame or like cauſe of ſeparation, there cannot be the ſame or like reaſon for ſeparating. In the one you cannot hold communion with the ſuppoſed good, but you muſt have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion alſo with the intollerably bad; and there the ſeparation is properly and directly from the intollerably bad, and but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally from the ſuppoſed good. But what is this to a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from or a non-communion with reformed Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where no ſuch intollerably evill-doers are to be found, from whom to withdraw or with whom to deny communion, would be a ſeparation properly, directly, and only from the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly good.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The caſe differs as much or rather much more, in reſpect of the communion it ſelfe. For in the Popiſh Aſſemblies, you cannot have communion in the Lords Supper it ſelfe (which is ſo eſſentiall a part of Church-communion) but you muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate in the ſuperſtition or Idolatry which is with them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably annexed to it: <hi>He that eats of the ſacrifice is partaker of the Altar,</hi> 1 Cor: 10.18. But in having communion with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Congregations of the Pedobaptiſts, there's no neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an actuall participation in any one act of ſuperſtition. For he that deemeth the ſprinkling or baptizing of an infant ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, may ſuſpend his communion in that action, and yet continue it in others. As our Lord Chriſt kept the Paſſeover a day or two before the generality of the Jewes, (for the day of his crucifixion, was but the day of their preparation to the Paſſeover, <hi>Joh:</hi> 19.14, 31.) they miſſing (as is conceived) the punctuall time of that feaſt; and yet denyed not his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them in other things wherein he and they were agreed. So that neither doth this <hi>Rev:</hi> 18.4. any wayes appeare to me a ſufficient ground for one godly Congregation to deny communion with another, upon account of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpecified, or any other like it.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41880:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But for ſuch as are baptized after faith, to hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with ſuch who have not been baptized otherwiſe then by infant ſprinkling, is as voyd of Scripture-precept and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-preſident, as is the ſeparation of godly from godly: and why then is not the one as unlawfull as the other?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Be it ſo as to particularity of precept or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: yet in this or any like caſe when any are in doubt between two difficulties, the way to come to a ſatisfactory reſolution which to incline to, is by diſcovering by which the peace, love, and edification of the Church of Chriſt, will be beſt promoted; for theſe ought to ſway us and carry us along with them, in all ſuch caſes wherein we are not bound to the contrary by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe rule. <hi>Let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to which you are called in one body,</hi> Col: 3.15. Let it rule, reigne, or umpire, as the word is rendered. It muſt then have the caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voyce when things otherwiſe are in an equapoiz; and as a King give Lawes in ſuch caſes. The law of love is the royall Law, <hi>James</hi> 2.8 it hath the ſoveraigne and commanding power over inferiour lawes of particular order. And edification muſt over-rule us in many caſes, as being that to which Church-ordinances and order are ſubordinate; as I ſhewed in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer argument. <hi>Let us therefore follow after the things that make for peace, and the things by which we may edifie one another, Rom:</hi> 14.19. If we are in doubt which to follow, this or that; here's our direction.</p>
                  <p>But now that the communion of differing Saints, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their difference when managed with a chriſtian ſpirit, tends abundantly more to peace, love and edification, then their ſeparation for their difference ſake would doe, is a thing that ſhines by its own light, and is evidenced in my former ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though we have no particular precept or preſident in the caſe objected, yet we have generall rules that reach i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſuch are they already named, and ſo is <hi>Mat:</hi> 12.7. <hi>I will have mercy, and not ſacrifice.</hi> Gal: 6.2. <hi>Bear ye one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt.</hi> Rom: 14. <hi>Him that is weak in the faith, receive ye.</hi> Rom: 15. <hi>We that are ſtrong, ought to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41880:31"/>bear the infirmities of the weake, and not to pleaſe our ſelves: and to receive one another, as Chriſt hath received us,</hi> ver: 7. 1 Cor: 14.26. <hi>Let all things be done to edifying;</hi> and the like: the face of which is ſet againſt dividing, ſeparating, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting one another for ſuch errours as are but Saints infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, amongſt which the miſtakes about Baptiſme in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie between them, muſt certainly be numbered.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>V <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THat practice which neceſſarily makes a ſchiſme in the body of Chriſt, is ſinfull.</p>
                  <p>But ſeparation of Saints from Saints upon account of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them, neceſſarily makes a ſchiſme in the body of Chriſt. Therefore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>That to make a ſchiſme in the body of Chriſt, is a ſinfull act in whomſoever found, is evident, becauſe its contrary to the declared will of the Lord, who would have no ſchiſme in the body, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.24, 25. <hi>God hath tempered the body together, having given more abundant honour to that part which lacked; that there ſhould be no ſchiſme in the body: but that all ſhould be one,</hi> Joh: 17.21. <hi>Keeping the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace,</hi> Eph: 4.3.</p>
                  <p>That for Saints to divide and ſeparate from Saints, is to make a ſchiſme in the body of Chriſt, is eaſie to underſtand. For thoſe that are indeed Saints, are all of them of the body of Chriſt, what ever their difference otherwiſe may be, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for them to ſeparate and rend one from another, is ſurely to make a ſchiſme in the body, if any thing be. And ſo they doe more eſpecially, when they refuſe communion with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Supper of the Lord. For as by their mutuall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion therein, their oneneſſe is in ſpeciall ſignified and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.17. ſo by their deniall of communion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that oneneſſe is denied: and what's this but ſchiſme in the formality of it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> When the godly are in their communion, mixt with others that are ungodly, and ſuch with whom communion is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41880:32"/>forbidden, then either to withdraw from ſuch godly ones, is no ſinfull ſchiſme; or elſe other of the Saints are neceſſitated to ſin, either in withdrawing from the Saints in ſuch mixt aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, or in holding communion with thoſe with whom com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is forbidden; which is an abſurdity not to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such a ſeparation is not made from the godly as ſcrupling their communion, could they have communion with them alone; but its made from thoſe, communion with whom is forbidden, and for their ſake only. And in all reaſon, the ſeparation muſt receive its denominatien from the cauſe whence it proceeds, and ſo it is not a ſeparation from thoſe that are of the body, but from thoſe that are not. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, this objection is irrelative to our queſtion touching the lawfulneſſe of communion between a godly Congregation of Anabaptiſts, and a godly and reformed Congregation of Pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Though we doe owne the godly Pedobaptiſts to be members of Chriſts-body, yet withall becauſe their viſible Church-ſtate and miniſtery, is founded in infant baptiſme, we cannot but in that reſpect judge them to be of the whoriſh ſtate, and our ſeparation from them, is not as they are of the body of Chriſt, but as they are members of the harlot: and ſo our ſchiſme from them, reſpects not their chriſtian, but their harlot or antichriſtian ſtate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. When you owne the godly Pedobaptiſts to be of Chriſts body, it is becauſe they are viſibly ſo, for upon no other account can they be knowne or acknowledged to be ſo. And I would have it ſeriouſly conſidered, whether it be not a contradiction to grant them to be members of Chriſts body, and yet to affirme them to be members of the harlot: and whether its poſſible for them to be of the Chriſtian and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſtate, both at once. No man can ſerve two Maſters that are contrary, <hi>Mat:</hi> 6.24. No more ſure can one be a member of two oppoſite bodyes at once. As by the ſame acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by which a man makes himſelfe a friend of the world, he makes himſelfe an enemy to God, <hi>James</hi> 4.4. So by the ſame
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41880:32"/>actions by which a man makes himſelfe a member of the harlot Church, he (for ought I know) cuts himſelfe off from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, or true Church. And the reaſon is clearly this; becauſe the myſticall harlot, when once ſhe comes to be ſo, receives her bill of divorce from the Lord, by which the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-union and relation becomes diſſolved, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 50.1. <hi>Jer:</hi> 3.8. <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 2.2, 5. And that which is true of the whole in this caſe, is true of every part, the wholeneſſe only excepted: if the harlot be under divorcement as ſuch, then all that make up that harlot ſtate are ſo. And therefore whilſt you acknowledge them members of Chriſts body, you cannot rationally repute them of the whoriſh ſtate.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is not every erronious opinion or ſuperſtitious practice that is found amongſt them of the whoriſh ſtate, that will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominate all thoſe to be of that ſtate that hold them, whilſt they are otherwiſe loyall to Chriſt in the mayne; no more then eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wanton or immodeſt word, looke, or geſture, will denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a woman to be a whore, who is otherwiſe loyall to her husband in the mayne. The good Kings, <hi>Solomon, Aſa,</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat,</hi> were guilty of a little ſpirituall immodeſty, in uſing, or at leaſt tolerating the high places, but did not come under a ſpirituall divorce from God thereby, as others did, who did that and more; nor did they thereby become unfit to be held communion with in other regular acts of Gods worſhip. There's a great deal of difference between that which is eſſentiall to the conſtituting of a ſtate, and other things which enter not the definition thereof. A bad man may doe many good things, and a good man many evill, by which neither are to be denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated good or bad, but by what they are and doe in the mayne, by what is predominant in them. So thoſe that are of the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſtate, may hold many of the ſame truths, and doe ſome of the ſame good deeds which a ſound member of Chriſts Church may doe, and yet not thereby be worthy the denomination of ſuch a member as long as their corruptions in doctrine, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and life, out-weigh theſe. And its as true that ſome that are not of the whoriſh ſtate, may be tainted with ſome of her errours and ſuperſtitions, which as to matter of conſtitution of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41880:33"/>ſtate, may be much over-ballanced by ſoundneſſe of faith, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of worſhip, and ſincerity of life in the mayne. We had need then to take heed of being raſh and bold in judging ſuch to be of the whoriſh ſtate, upon account of ſome under-degree of ſpirituall lightneſſe, that our conſciences tell us, are in the ſtate of grace, and Spouſe-like, love Chriſt more then they doe any other. It would provoke even a good man to have his wife called whore, whom he knowes guilty onely of ſome leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer faults: and ſurely it does no leſſe diſpleaſe the Lord to have ſuch as are eſpouſed to him, to be ſo dealt with.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It remains then that I adde one thing more for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating my anſwer to the objection, and that is; That com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Saints that are in ſome things erronious and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, does not inferre a communion in the errour or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition it ſelfe, whilſt you bear your witneſſe againſt it. This is plaine, otherwiſe the ſtrong muſt have been guilty of the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and ſuperſtition of the weak Saints in the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> by holding that communion with them to which the Apoſtle preſſed them, <hi>Rom:</hi> 14 and 15 Chapters. Elſe the few names in <hi>Sardis</hi> alſo, could not have kept their garments unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> led in holding communion with perſons ſo much defiled, as the reſt there were, which yet they did, <hi>Rev:</hi> 3.4. It followes then, that ſuch involuntary errours in perſons as doe conſiſt with the viſibility of true grace, doe not render communion with them unlawfull, in ſuch things which are not of themſelve unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: we may hold communion with them in their graces, and in their duties, though not in their errours. Though you may and ought to withdraw your communion in ſuch acts wherein you are ſure they have not communion with Chriſt, yet you may not doe ſo in thoſe in which you know they have.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>VI <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF the godly Anabaptiſts, doe hold communion with the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pedobaptiſts, in that which is ſignified by breaking of bread in the Lords Supper, Then it is not unlawfull but their duty for them to hold communion in breaking of bread it ſelfe which is the ſigne.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41880:33"/>
                  <p>But the godly Anabaptiſts and godly Pedobaptiſts, doe hold communion one with another in that which is ſignified by breaking of bread in the Lords Supper. Therefore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>That which is ſignified by the uſe of the bread and cup in the Lords Supper, is ſhewed by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.16. to wit, communion in the body and blood of Chriſt. And that the godly of both ſorts, to wit, of Pedobaptiſts and Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts have communion by faith in the body and blood of Jeſus Chriſt, eating the ſame ſpirituall meat, and drinking the ſame ſpirituall drink, I think will not be denyed, and therefore needs no proofe. But that which requires a further demonſtration, is the Major propoſition. The reaſon then why its not unlawfull but a duty for thoſe to hold communion in the ſigne, that have communion in the ſubſtance, or thing ſignified, is</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſo to doe anſwers the end of the ordinance: whereas a denyall of communion in the ſigne where it is held in ſubſtance, would croſſe the very end of the ordinance. The ſigne is ordained but for the thing ſake unto which it does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late: the outward communion in the ſigne bread and wine, is appointed to ſignifie and increaſe the communicants inward and ſpirituall communion in the body &amp; blood of Jeſus Chriſt, and their unity thereby, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.16, 17. And therefore where the thing to be ſignified is in being, (which is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Chriſts body and blood) there to deny the uſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the meanes appointed by God to ſignifie it, (to wit, communion in the Supper) would be to croſſe the very end of that ordinance. If partners that have a joynt ſtock in trade, and ſo a joynt intereſt in it, ſhould refuſe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and declare to each other their reſpective intereſts, by ſuch ſignes as are cuſtomary among men in ſuch caſes, it would be accounted a great piece of injuſtice. And is it any leſſe then a piece of ſpirituall injuſtice for thoſe that have a joynt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Chriſts body and blood, to refuſe to acknowledge and declare it to each other, and before all, by ſuch a ſigne which the Lord hath appointed for that purpoſe?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe mens right to the ſigne, proceeds from their right to the thing ſignified. As thoſe that have a right to ſuch
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41880:34"/>or ſuch an eſtate in land, have thereby a right to the deeds and evidences by which ſuch a right is to be declared, ſo thoſe that have a right to the body and blood of Chriſt in their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving effects, have thereby right to the Lords Supper, as an evidence appointed by God by which ſuch their right is to be declared and acknowledged. And therefore as a detaining of ſuch evidence from him who by having right to the Land, hath right to the evidence, would be an injury; even ſo a detaining the Lords Supper from him who by having right to the body and blood of Chriſt, hath right to the Lords Supper as an evidence and ſigne thereof, would be an injury like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And as ſpirituall things are of more value then tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſo an injury in them is greater then an injury in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Its againſt common reaſon and equity to grant them to have communion with us in the greater and better part, and to deny it them in the leſſe; the greater ſtill including the leſſe. But to be partakers of like precious faith with us, and by that to eat of that <hi>fleſh which is meat indeed,</hi> and <hi>to drink of that blood which is drink indeed, and to drink into one and the ſame Spirit,</hi> as both ſorts of godly ones doe, is certainly to have, hold, and enjoy communion together in the greater, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more ſpirituall and more ſubſtantiall part of it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to deny it in the outſide and letter of it, which is farre leſſe conſiderable, ſeemes very incongruous and contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41880:34"/>
               <head>An exhortation to unity, peace, and concord.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſaid this much by way of Argument touching the unlawfulneſſe of Separation, and the lawfulneſſe of communion between Saints, though of different perſwaſion; I ſhall now adde a little more to quicken the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren on both ſides, to unity, concord, and peace; which have been too long divided and too much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged one from another. For this end let it be ſeriouſly conſidered;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the heart and ſoule of our Lord Jeſus, is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſet upon the unity, not onely of the Saints of this or that particular and different perſwaſion, but of all thoſe that believe through his Apoſtles word, how different ſoever in opinion and perſwaſion, they otherwiſe may be. And this appeares; 1. In that Chriſt made it matter of his ſolemne addreſſe unto his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo it might be. <hi>John</hi> 17.20, 21. <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo which ſhall believe on me through their word: that they</hi> [all] <hi>may be one.</hi> 2. In that it was the ſubject matter of one of his laſt requeſts to his father now he was about to leave the world. Thoſe things uſually are moſt upon the heart, which men bring forth at ſuch a time when they are ready to die. 3. And which is yet more: among all the things which concerne the Saints here in this world, he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles out this of their unity, as that which was moſt upon his heart to form into a ſolemne requeſt unto his father on their behalfe. There are upon the matter but two things which he prayed for in the behalfe of all thoſe that ſhould believe, contained in that part of his prayer which you have from <hi>v.</hi> 20. to the end of <hi>John</hi> 17. the one of which reſpecting their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condition in the other world; and that is that they might be with him where he is, to behold his glory: and the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting their preſent condition in this world; and that is that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41880:35"/>they all might be one. So then although there be many other things wherein the comfort and welfare of the Saints in this world are concerned, yet their unity and agreement is that which Chriſt ſingles out from among all the reſt, as being moſt upon his heart, and as one would think, ſhould therefore be that thing wherein their peace and welfare is moſt concerned. 4. Its further moſt worthy obſervation, that among all the things which Chriſt prayed for in this prayer recorded in <hi>John</hi> 17. he does not inſiſt ſo much upon any one thing as this of unity among the Saints. And therefore you have him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling this petition againe and againe, and mentioning it a third and a fourth time alſo, as you may ſee in <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 21, 22, 23. As if his heart were ſo full of it, as that it could not be all brought out at once but by degrees: it was out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his heart, that he abounded ſo much in this one peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>And is the heart of our dear Lord ſo much in it? and ſhall not the heart of every one to whom he is dear, be much in it too! Can you follow a better pattern, or write after a better copie? It is without all doubt that the more you have of the ſame Spirit that dwelt in him, the more it will enlarge your hearts this way in conformity to this heavenly temper that was ſo eminent in him. And the more you ſhall finde your hearts run out to this thing, as Chriſts did, the more ſhall you be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with an aſſurance of your dwelling in him and he in you, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.13. <hi>Hereby know we that we dwell in him, and he in us, becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit.</hi> And what way is there in all the world for you to indeer your ſelves to Chriſt more, then in being found according to his owne heart? Doe not good diſpoſition'd parents, take moſt pleaſure in thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are moſt of their own temper? and ſo does Chriſt in thoſe that are moſt like him. How great a praiſe was it to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to be ſaid to be a man after Gods owne heart! (<hi>Acts</hi> 13.22.) and I am ſure it will be your glory in this, to be men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſts owne heart. Did Chriſt pray and pray ſo earneſtly for this thing, that all that are believers ſhould be one? why then let thoſe that would be like him, and profeſſe to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41880:35"/>of him, doe ſo too. And not onely pray, but earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by uſe of meanes to bring that to paſſe which we ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly pray for. If men were but as willing and deſirous to pleaſe Chriſt Jeſus, and to gratifie the deſire of his ſoule in this, as they ſeeme to be in ſome other things towards which he hath given no ſuch apparent manifeſtation of his affection, we ſhould certainly have things at another paſſe among the people of God, then now they are. And I pray you why ſhould we not be moſt for that in which he moſt delights?</p>
               <p n="2">2. And therefore conſider further, that love and kindneſſe and cleaving of heart, and affection of Saints to Saints, is that which Chriſt among other things moſt deſires, as being that grace wherein he hath moſt abounded towards them, and by which they will be moſt Chriſt-like, and ſo moſt Chriſtian. As the greatneſſe of his affection to union among the Saints, was expreſſed by his praying for it againe and againe in the ſame prayer, ſo does his great longing after love among all his Diſciples, manifeſtly appeare by his fervent and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate preſſing and enjoyning it againe and againe and againe in one and the ſame ſpeech or Sermon, and in that alſo which was his farewell Sermon when he was now leaving them and the world, wherein to be ſure he would inſiſt moſt upon that which lay moſt at his heart. And this he did with a note or ſigne of ſpeciall appropriation fixed upon it, <hi>[my comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement]</hi> as if that were more eſpecially his and had more of his heart in it then others. <hi>John</hi> 15.12. <hi>This is [my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,] that ye love one another, as I have loved you.</hi> John 13.34. <hi>A new commandement I give unto you, that ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye alſo love one another,</hi> John 15.17. <hi>Theſe things I command you that ye love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if Chriſts heart ran moſt upon this, they are in no wiſe like to pleaſe him, that by contending for ſome particular point, which hath not it may be the tenth (if any) of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of his minde, will and affection in it, which this hath, doe make a breach upon and hinder this. It was ſaid, <hi>Hath the Lord as great delight in burnt-offerings and ſacrifices, as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41880:36"/>in obeying the voyce of the Lord?</hi> 1 Sam: 15.22. And may be ſaid, hath Chriſt Jeſus any ſuch delight in your ſacrificing a great part of the peace, charity, and comfort of the Saints, upon ſome controverted order or doctrine in the Church, as he hath in obeying him in this great command of his, that carries ſo much of his heart in it? For them that think ſo, let them againe hearken to what he ſaith, <hi>Mat:</hi> 9.13. <hi>Goe ye and learne what that meaneth, I will have mercy and not ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. And to love him with all the heart — and to love his neighbour as himſelfe, is more then all whole burnt-offerings and ſacrifices,</hi> Mark 12.33. And yet ſacrifice was more expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded, then moſt of thoſe things that are the bone of contention among the people of God at this day. Love, mercy, and judgement, are the weightier matters of the Law, and therefore may by no meanes be thruſt out by thoſe that are leſſe, as too commonly they are. What ever goes up, to be ſure Religion and Chriſtianity goes downe when charity goes downe. Therefore <hi>[above all theſe things] put on chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is the bond of perfectneſſe,</hi> Col: 3.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Adde hereto another very weighty conſideration, which is, That what ever knowledge you have of the minde of God, and what ever zeale you expreſſe for any truth of God, either concerning faith or practice, yet if while you hold faſt other things, you let goe charity, your knowledge, your zeale, though it were to the loſing of your life for truth, will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit you nothing. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13.2, 3. <hi>Though I underſtand all my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and all knowledge, and have not charity, I am nothing. And though I give my body to be burned, and have not chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> And left you ſhould think it meant of that charity which conſiſts in relieving of the poore, and not of that which conſiſts in cleaving to and delighting in Saints as Saints, brethren as brethren; he ſaith alſo; <hi>Though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poore, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing,</hi> 1 Cor: 13.3. All which neerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes ſuch to minde, that are more carefull and tender leſt ſome other controverted truth ſhould ſuffer, then charity, brotherly love and concord, ſhould ſuffer; and care not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41880:36"/>what rents and diviſions they make among the people of God, ſo that they may but propagate their particular opinion. <hi>If there be bitter zeale</hi> (as the Dutch tranſlation hath it) <hi>glory not</hi> of thy knowledge, <hi>and lie not againſt the truth,</hi> as if thou wert the Goſpels friend, when by ſuch a carriage thou art an enemy to it, <hi>James</hi> 3.14.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Your contentions and diviſions, if you maintaine them, they will deſtroy you in your ſpirituall trade, and keep you from thriving by the means and opportunities of grace you enjoy. It was a ſad thing wherewith the Apoſtle charged the Corinthian Chriſtians, that when they came together to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe themſelves in the holy ordinances of the Lord, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be not for the better, but for the worſe, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.17. But upon what doth he charge this dreadfull miſcarriage of their going backward in their trade, and of growing worſe and worſe by what was provided for their welfare? Verily it was their diviſions that was the cauſe of all this miſchiefe. <hi>Ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Now in this that I declare unto you, I praiſe you not, that you come together not for the better, but for the worſe.</hi> How does that appeare? <hi>For firſt of all, when ye come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Church, I hear that there be diviſions among you.</hi> Concluding that ſo it muſt be that their diviſions would occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion their decay and loſſe under the richeſt enjoyments other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; for they abounded exceedingly with ſpirituall gifts, <hi>Chap:</hi> 1.5, 7. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. The truth is, they eat out the very heart of Religion: men may grow rich in a form of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and expreſſe a great deal of zeal for the out-ſide of Religion; and in the mean while be languiſhing in the very vitalls of Chriſtianity, while they live in diviſion and ſtrife: <hi>For where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion, and every evill worke,</hi> James 3.16. This will be as a worme at the root of your tree that will keep it from proſpering, what ever coſt you otherwiſe beſtow upon it.</p>
               <p>If then you have any minde to keep up Religion in heart among you, and not to have your wine to become as water, having loſt its heart and ſpirit: If you would have the Goſpel ordinances to yeild you their increaſe, and all your Religion
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41880:37"/>not to degenerate into form: If you would yeild God an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and pleaſant fruit of all his coſt, and not ſuch as is ſtarvie, harſh, and unſavory: If you would not <hi>turn the fruit of righteouſneſſe into hemlock:</hi> If you would be freed from ſuch a predominant diſtemper, as will hinder your ſpirituall relliſh, and convert your food into a noxious humour, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject you to a languiſhing diſeaſe in the midſt of plenty; Then abandon contention, and lay aſide diviſion, and with a ſpirit of love, meekneſſe, and peace, communicate your diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thoughts, and patiently bear with a conſcientious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If you would ſecure the Proteſtant Religion and Cauſe from being a prey to the lurking Papiſt, and from being ſwol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of Atheiſts, Libertines, Apoſtates, Quakers, by all which it is at this day ſorely aſſaulted and dangerouſly beſet, then unite heart, and head, and hand, to make one ſtrength to withſtand them, <hi>that no man take your Crowne.</hi> For your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions incourageth them in their deſignes, invites them to attempt upon you, and prepares many to fall in with them. So that as long as you keep up your diviſions, they will grow upon you, and get ground, and by little and little draw away your ſtrength, and in concluſion over-maſter you, if by uniting you prevent them not: <hi>A kingdome divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelfe, cannot ſtand,</hi> Mat: 12.25. And therefore if you ſhall ſo labour to maintaine one particular Fort, as in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it you looſe the whole Nation; I mean ſo maintaine a particular opinion in Religion, as by dividing about it, to endanger the loſſe of the whole; you will ſhew your ſelves (according to the proverb) to be peny wiſe and pound fooliſh: and will Chriſt ever thanke you for ſuch a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice?</p>
               <p n="6">6. The more you knit together in love for the great truth ſake that dwelleth in you, the greater and richer <hi>[aſſurance of underſtanding]</hi> ſhall you have in the Myſtery of the Father and of Chriſt. <hi>Col:</hi> 2.2. <hi>Being knit together in love, unto all riches of the full aſſurance of underſtanding,</hi> &amp;c. Being knit together in love, bears the relation of a means, to the full
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41880:37"/>aſſurance of underſtanding, as the end. Its one thing to know what the Goſpel treats of; and another thing to know aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that all that which the Goſpel treats of, is true and is no lie: Many have much of the former, which as it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, have little of the latter. And yet ſome too, that have leſſe of the former then others, but more love, have more of the latter then they. The Lord takes ſuch pleaſure in the cloſe cleaving of the hearts of his ſervants one to another, as that he crownes it with this aſſurance of underſtanding: <hi>root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and grounding them in love;</hi> and eſtabliſhing them in the preſent truth. Hence I ſuppoſe it is that you have many who though they have leſſe knowledge, yet having more love, ſtand faſt in the truth, whilſt others that have a great deal more knowledge but little or no charity, are turned up by the rootes. Its therefore preſcribed by way of remedy or preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt <hi>being toſſed to and fro, and carried about by every winde of doctrine, and ſlight of men that lie in waite to deceive, that the truth be ſpoken in love:</hi> that love, which is a uniting grace, accompany mens knowledge and profeſſion of truth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14, 15. And truely the full aſſurance of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to have the minde and conſcience eſtabliſhed in the truth in theſe ſhaking and declining times, is a prize worth the running for, eſpecially in ſo pleaſant a path, as love and union of heart and affection is.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The more unanimous and harmonious you are, the more perfect you will be. You have much talke of perfection, and many pretend to it that are farre from it; but to be ſure, its the mark and aime of every ſincere Chriſtian, and I think does conſiſt in nothing more next our love to God, then in the Saints love and unity. This is the cry of the Scripture: <hi>That they may be made</hi> [perfect in one] <hi>John</hi> 17.23. <hi>Be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one minde, live in peace,</hi> 2 Cor: 13.11. <hi>Above all theſe, put on charity, which is the bond of [perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,]</hi> Col: 3.14. <hi>If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his love is [perfected in us]</hi> 1 John 4.12. <hi>And love is the fulfilling of the Law,</hi> Rom: 13.10. Which is more then can be ſaid of any controverted opinion among the Saints: and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41880:38"/>therefore you miſtake your way, if in your purſuit of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you turn aſide from love and unity, and make a faction to cry up ſome ſingle opinion which is not of the eſſence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The harmony and unity of the Saints, is a lovely object to behold, and an excellent ornament of your Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and very taking with others. <hi>Behold, how good, and how pleaſant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity!</hi> Pſal. 133.1. And while the believers <hi>were of one heart, and of one ſoule, great grace was upon them all: and the Lord added to the Church daily, ſuch as ſhould be ſaved,</hi> Acts 4.32, 33. &amp; 2.47. Which cannot be ſaid of any particular opinion extra-eſſentiall to Chriſtianity: and therefore there's not that weight to be laid on it, as is to be in preſerving the harmony, unity, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Saints. But alas the contrary, works the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary effect of diſgrace and diſparagement to our holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and rendring it and the friends of it, leſſe deſireable; of which theſe dayes afford us more of the experience, then of the lovely, beautifull, and deſireable effects of the Saints harmony.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If you prize your comfort, prize agreement: for thoſe that are living and not dead or benumb'd members of Chriſts body, cannot but be pained with the rending of one member from another of that body of which they are: <hi>If one member ſuffer, all the members ſuffer with it,</hi> 1 Cor: 12.26. Was it not a ſorrowfull ſight to ſee the man in <hi>Mark</hi> 5.5. cutting himſelfe with ſtones, and an argument that he was poſſeſſed with an evil ſpirit? Every one will grant it. And pray you how much leſſe dolefull is it to ſee the Saints, children of the living God, cutting and wounding themſelves; for ſo they doe, when they cut and wound one another; for they are <hi>members one of another,</hi> Rom: 12.5. Alas, how unnaturall is it! for <hi>who ever hated his owne fleſh?</hi> Eph: 5.29. Certainly where thus it is, its an argument they are under a ſpirituall frenzie and madneſſe, and ſo are objects of very great co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſeration, and are an occaſion of much trouble and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in their Fathers houſe. But O the <hi>comfort of love,</hi> (as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41880:38"/>the Apoſtle phraſeth it, <hi>Phil:</hi> 2.1.) the pleaſure of peace, and the delight of harmony; like a well tuned Inſtrument, where there is no Jarring. <hi>Behold how good and how [pleaſant] a thing it is, for brethren to dwell together in unity.</hi> Its not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good and profitable, but pleaſant and comfortable alſo, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 33.1. A great part of a Chriſtians comfort in this world, lies in his communion with Saints. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Saints and excellent, were all his delight,</hi> Pſal: 16.3. And therefore a breach in this, muſt needs make a great breach upon a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians comfort.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The more you are for union and reconciliation, and making of peace, the more you will be like God, whoſe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſſe and grace inclines him to ſeeke after thoſe that are at a farre greater diſtance from him, then any of the Saints are from one another: <hi>He is in Chriſt, reconciling the world unto himſelfe,</hi> 2 Cor: 5.19. Yea this is that <hi>good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which he hath purpoſed in himſelfe, that in the diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fulneſſe of times, he might gather together in one, all things in Chriſt, both which are in heaven, and which are on earth, even in him,</hi> Eph: 1.9, 10. Sin had divided and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his creatures in their affections as well from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as from him; but the ſoule of the Almighty was ſo ſet upon their reconciliation and re-union, that he ſends his Son Jeſus Chriſt in due time, to gather them together into one in Chriſt as their common head. And for that end alſo he appointed the miniſtry, and from time to time furniſheth them with gifts, Firſt, to perſwade men to be reconciled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, (2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.19.) and then to bring them all to unity in the faith and knowledge of the Son of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. This God hath done to procure reconciliation and peace. And therefore <hi>bleſſed are the peace-makers, for they ſhall be called the children of God,</hi> Mat: 5.9. They whoſe hearts, and heads, and hands, are in it, that labour at it with deſire to effect it, to bring men, eſpecially the Saints to termes of peace and good agreement, they tread in their fathers ſteps, follow the ſame work, deſigne, affect, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour at the ſame thing; and therefore well may they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41880:39"/>his children; <hi>and followers of God as deare children,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 5.1. And being his children, come under a great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe indeed, having ſuch a father, whoſe affection and power for their advancement, hath no bounds but what an infinite wiſdome ſets. And truely if this will not ſet our hearts on fire to be at this worke, I know not what will. If then you deſire to make good unto your owne ſoules the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of your Son-ſhip and relation to God upon the beſt termes, it will not be enough for you to be your ſelves per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to reconciliation and agreement with your diſſenting brethren, but to be active and buſie in procuring it in others where its wanting. For otherwiſe though you may be peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, yet you will have little to denominate you <hi>[peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Its the way to have God with you and delight in you. He is ſo great a lover of peace and concord, that he will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes make one at this work; you ſhall be ſure to have his company and preſence, both whilſt you abide in it, and when you lift up your heart, hand, and tongue to promote it. <hi>Live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you,</hi> 2 Cor: 13.11. Such ſhall have God with them as a God of peace, ſpeaking peace to them, evidencing himſelfe to be at peace with them. I appeal to their conſciences who have knowne the difference of living in a divided ſtate, and of living in unity with all Saints, and of making themſelves ſervants to ſo good a worke as to reconcile Saints, whether they have not more inward peace from God, and a richer te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his love in the time of their reconciliation, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and profeſſed conjunction with all Saints, then they had in the time of their diſtance from many of them. Its moſt true that <hi>he that dwells moſt in love, dwells moſt with God and God with him,</hi> 1 Joh: 4.12, 16. And how they can expect peace from God, that doe not live in peace with all thoſe with whom God is at peace, I know not. Eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt hath told them, that <hi>if they from their heart, doe not forgive their brothers treſpaſſes, that then neither will their heavenly father forgive theirs,</hi> Mat. 6.14. &amp; 18.35.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41880:39"/>And what kinde of forgiveneſſe that is that can ſtand with puniſhing their brethren for involuntary miſpriſions, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting them from their communion, and carrying themſelves towards them as if they were none of the ſame houſe, but children of another father, I deſire may be deeply ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thoſe whom it concernes.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle exhorting the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to this very duty, backs it with no leſſe then ſeven motives or reaſon, <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</hi> For 1. <hi>There is one body;</hi> and 2. <hi>one Spirit, even as</hi> 3. <hi>ye are called in one hope of your calling:</hi> 4. <hi>One Lord;</hi> 5. <hi>one faith;</hi> 6. <hi>one Baptiſme;</hi> 7. <hi>one God and father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> Each of which have very much in them to prevaile with the divided hearts and unpeaceable ſpirits of profeſſors, to lay aſide their warres and contentions, which are but the off-ſpring of their owne luſts. <hi>James</hi> 4.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.15. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.3. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.20. But I would not be tedious, and therefore ſhall not inlarge upon them, hoping that what hath been already ſaid, cannot but come home to the conſcience of all thoſe whoſe uncharitableneſſe hath not exceedingly hardened their heart.</p>
               <p>Neither doe I doubt but that every one will be ready to acknowledge this which I have been exhorting to, to be every Chriſtians duty, and will profeſſe their great affection to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and peace. But alas, experience ſhewes, that it is too commonly with this proviſo, or inward reſerve, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo as that they may have unity and peace upon their owne termes: uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the truth, as they call it, and that truth, their particular opinion, upon which diviſion is built. The meaning of which is, that they would maintaine peace with all, provided that none would oppoſe them in their opinion, but ſay as they ſay: having that in their mouthes, <hi>Jer:</hi> 15.19. <hi>Let them returne to thee, but return not thou unto them;</hi> which they wofully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe whiles they apply it to leſſer differences. But if unity and peace, and communion too, were not to be had and held but upon ſuch termes, what uſe would there be (in relation to different opinions in leſſer matters,) of thoſe many exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41880:40"/>of <hi>bearing the infirmities of the weake; of long-ſuffering and forbearing one another in love;</hi> of <hi>bearing one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens;</hi> of <hi>not looking every man on his owne things, but every man alſo on the things of others?</hi> Rom: 15.1. Epheſ: 4.2. Col: 3.13. Gal: 6.2. Phil: 2.4. A cordiall and peaceable communion, and forbearance are not inconſiſtent. Union, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and peace, muſt be kept and maintained upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians agreement in fundamentalls of faith and holineſſe, when in the meane while, bearing and forbearing muſt be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in relation to thoſe things wherein they otherwiſe differ. Which being the plain Scripture-road, its much to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that ſo many who ſeeme zealous of the Scripture-pattern, ſhould miſſe it.</p>
               <p>Therefore I beſeech all thoſe that love the Lord Jeſus, and that love to doe that which pleaſeth him, that you ſuffer not thoſe few and leſſer things wherein you differ, to prevaile more with you to keep at a diſtance, and to deny your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to one another, then thoſe many, great and precious things wherein you are agreed, to bring and binde you cloſe together, and freely to afford your Chriſtian communion one to another. Is it reaſonable or hath ſuch a thing been heard of in other caſes, that the minor vote ſhould carry it againſt the major? Lay aſide then all prejudice, ſtiffneſſe, and ſelfe-will'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and count it your glory that you can ſeeke to others to receive you into cloſer communion, before they ſeeke to you. And in your proſecution of this work of reconciling diſtant brethren, doe not be beaten off, by others hanging off; but reckon it ſo choice a piece of generation-work in theſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding times, as that you can hardly lift up your heart, your tongue, your hand, to ſuch another.</p>
               <p>And you that are Miniſters of Chriſt, who is <hi>the Prince of peace,</hi> and of the Goſpel, which is <hi>the Goſpel of peace,</hi> and whoſe work is <hi>to guide mens feet into the way of peace,</hi> and the end of whoſe calling is, to bring <hi>all to the unity of the faith and knowledge of the Son of God:</hi> be intreated Reverend and beloved, to take heed of making the breach wider, and by any undue repreſentations or aggravations, to frighten Saints of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41880:40"/>different perſwaſions, from coming neere one another: but to perſwade to chriſtian moderation and forbearance, to a treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another with a ſpirit of meekneſſe, and an over-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one another with love, and herein to approve your ſelves as patterns. And in ſo doing, you ſhall finde more peace in your owne ſoules, and procure more in the Churches, and finde a greater ſucceſſe in your Miniſtry, make better tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Chriſtians, and ſet a more glorious Crowne upon the head of the Goſpel, then otherwiſe you are ever like to doe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
